<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of romances and their original by Monsieur Huet ; translated out of French.</title>
            <title>Traitté de l'origine des romans</title>
            <author>Huet, Pierre-Daniel, 1630-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3301</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38997</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18204177</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18204177</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107064</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44891)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107064)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1125:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of romances and their original by Monsieur Huet ; translated out of French.</title>
                  <title>Traitté de l'origine des romans</title>
                  <author>Huet, Pierre-Daniel, 1630-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Battersby, for S. Heyrick ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: Romances, and their original.</note>
                  <note>Licensed: October 21, 1671; Robert L'Estrange.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fiction --  History and criticism.</term>
               <term>Romance fiction --  History and criticism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107064:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF Romances AND THEIR ORIGINAL.</p>
            <p>By Monſieur <hi>HUET.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Battersby,</hi> for <hi>S. Heyrick,</hi> at <hi>Grays Inn</hi> Gate in <hi>Holborn.</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:107064:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed,</hi> October 21. 1671.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:107064:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:107064:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107064:3"/>
            <head>THE Tranſlator TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>AS our Manners and People are refin'd, Romances alſo hold pace with us, and by the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees arrive to perfection. <hi>Giants, Dragons,</hi> and <hi>Enchanted Caſtles,</hi> which made ſo much noiſe in Romances of former times, are now no longer heard of. The Compoſers do now conſult Nature, and endeavour to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit her true and lively Portraict in all their works, and ſo linck Inſtruction with Delight, that while the Reader gapes for this, he ſwallows both; they cajole
<pb facs="tcp:107064:4"/>and ſurprize him into Vertue, and make him good when he never dreams on't. But it is not my Province to plead for Romances, be they good or bad, ſince they are now ſo much in vogue in the World, and make ſo conſiderable a part of the politer Learning: 'tis preſumed the Ingenious have a Curioſity, and deſire a more perfect account of them, then poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hitherto they have met withall.</p>
            <p>The generality are ſo much in the dark about theſe matters, they neither know whence they ſpring, nor how they got the name of Romances. The two <hi>Italian</hi> Authors, cited in this Treatiſe, were it ſhould ſeem diligent enough in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearches: yet you will find what pitiful conjectures they were forced upon, and how wide they ſhoot from the mark, while one would derive it from <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the other from <hi>Rheyms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will find in our Author, beſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s his great learning and acquaintance with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, a critical wit and correct Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb facs="tcp:107064:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>many inſtances whereof are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playd as he traverſes <hi>Aegypt, Phoenicia, Arabia, Perſia, Syria,</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> in purſuance of his deſign: for our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is not content with <hi>Suidas,</hi> and <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and what other Magazines of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Monuments are found in <hi>Europe;</hi> but he ranſacks the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and makes the <hi>Oriental</hi> Libraries contributary.</p>
            <p>After our Author has taken ſurvey of theſe people, and conſidered their Wit, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination and Genius, and critiziſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Writings and Romances, he deſcendes in courſe <hi>to the famous Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Tricca, Heliodorus;</hi> whom he avows to have excelled all whoever went before him; and among other things takes notice of the ſingular Modeſty, obſerved religiouſly throughout his Work, though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay too ſuperſtitiouſly. For I find the Criticks are not well pleaſed that he ſhould make <hi>Theagenes</hi> give the fair <hi>Chariclea</hi> a box o'th'Ear, once when ſhe would have kiſt him: that have Lovers
<pb facs="tcp:107064:5"/>to do, ſay they, with his Epiſcopal ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues? the toyings and little freedoms of Lovers and the reverence of Biſhops ſuit but ill together; a Veſtal Chaſtity is none of the accompliſhments of an <hi>Hero,</hi> whoſe Love is above theſe ſcrupulous formalities which clog his Noble emotions and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable tranſports. They conclude that he had better have burnt his Book ten times over, then have made his <hi>Hero</hi> ſo abſurd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guilty, and left ſo vile an aſperſion on his Name.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Heliodorus</hi> Romances degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, and yielded to that common fate which ſhortly after fell upon good Letters; and of Natural, Exact and Probable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Wild, Groteſque and Chymerical; and ſo continued till of late days Monſieur <hi>d'Urfee</hi> took Pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Hand, and preſented the World with his <hi>Aſtrea;</hi> which our Author avers to be the moſt perfect piece that ever was Writ in its kind. For all this, he eſcapes the Criticks no better then <hi>Heliodorus:</hi> what notion, ſay they, had
<pb facs="tcp:107064:5"/>he of <hi>bien-ſeance,</hi> when he makes his <hi>Heroine Aſtrea</hi> one of the three Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardeſſes, who are diſcovered all naked to <hi>Celadon?</hi> was this confiſtent with her honour? or had not ſhe otherwiſe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient wherewith to complete her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Silvander,</hi> ſay they, is made a philiſopher to good purpoſe; brought from the famous <hi>School of the Maſſilians</hi> to turn Shepheard, and in this habit and condition to read Philoſophical Lectures, and deliver ſuch profound notions, as might turn the Brain, and confound all the Shepheards in Chriſtendom: And is allowed the opportunity to diſcover his Talent, and talk wiſely, but once in all his life time, and that is when nobody hears him.</p>
            <p>Our Author next takes notice of Madamoiſelle <hi>de Scudery,</hi> to whom the World is obliged for the <hi>Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Baſſa, Grand Cyrus,</hi> and <hi>Clelia;</hi> the worth of all which pieces the
<pb facs="tcp:107064:6"/>Reader cannot be ignorant of; I ſhall therefore onely preſent the Reader with ſome cavils or exceptions, which are made againſt ſome particulars in them. Some object that her ſo <hi>Illuſtrious Baſſa</hi> is no very good Chriſtian, and that it was no part of an <hi>Heroick</hi> vertue to diſſemble his Religion. His <hi>Horns</hi> ſhould have been concealed and not his Religion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they are made moſt ſhamefully notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: to make the <hi>Hero</hi> a Cuckold (ſay they) is ſuch on enormity, as but too much bewrays the ſex of the <hi>Author.</hi> She very franckly gives him a Wife, who (make him thankful) was no Novice, a Woman of expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, andone who after three Moneths a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boad in the <hi>Seraglio</hi> gave him to judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe had needed any of his inſtructions.</p>
            <p>They ſay likewiſe, that whoever had taught this Author her <hi>Geography,</hi> had cheated her extremely. The <hi>Fleet</hi> of this <hi>Baſſa</hi> departed from the Port at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and at or about the end of three Weeks after were ſeen Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caoling
<pb facs="tcp:107064:6"/>in the <hi>Caſpian Sea;</hi> 'twas mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily Sayled, in about three weeks time four hundred Leagues by Land; what mortal Ships could do the like in theſe days? She had conſulted ſome <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge Burgeſs</hi> to make the High-ways Navigable.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Grand Cyrus</hi> too, ſay they, is as injuriouſly dealt withall. For all his Toyl, Travail, and Fatigue, all his Trophees and Conqueſts, which he Sacrifices to <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane;</hi> he is like to have but a ſorry bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain of her, ſhe having been ſtoln away four times ere ſhe came to his hands. The <hi>Grand Cyrus</hi> muſt be ſo credulous as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſhe eſcapes pure and untouched from all theſe <hi>Raviſhers;</hi> or elſe this mighty <hi>Hero</hi> muſt be content with their leavings. Grant ſhe were Chaſte, theſe were too un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable proofs of her vertue; for once peradventure ſhe might come off clear, but relapſes are always mortal in theſe caſes. Her Honour might defend her the firſt aſſault, but the ſecond bears down all,
<pb facs="tcp:107064:7"/>is not to be reſiſted by a Fort already ſhaken, or by ſo frayl materials as Fleſh and Blood.</p>
            <p>Neither (ſay they) has this <hi>Author</hi> been more favourable to her own Sex. <hi>Clelia</hi> has as much cauſe to complain of hard uſage, in aſſigning her ſuch a paul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Gallant as <hi>Aronces.</hi> Never a <hi>youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Brother of Normandy</hi> could leave a meaner <hi>Idea</hi> of his perſon and vertue, then the <hi>Heroe</hi> of this Romance. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe one who has neither Page nor Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page; one in a greaſie Buff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Doublet, who changes his Crabat but once in eight days, whoſe fortune has no eſtabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhment, who ſpunges upon his friends, dining to day with one, next day with another, and climbes up three Stories h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gh to Bed at Night; This is the Portraict of <hi>Aronces.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe forſooth he was Son to <hi>Porſenna, King of the Hetrurians,</hi> (whoſe whole incomes ſcarce amounted to ten thouſand pounds <hi>per annum</hi> and who at one whiſtle could call all his Subjects together) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lelia</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:107064:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>muſt be made his Conqueſt. If (ſay they) it coſt an Author ought to rig out his <hi>Hero</hi> in good Cloathes and handſome Equipage, to Lodge him in a ſumptuous Palace, and provide him a plentiful Table, it then might be preſumed that none would tick with him for ſo much; but conſidering that all this expenſe is onely imagination, 'tis ſtrange that any ſhould be ſuch a nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of it, and deny ſo ſmall a matter to an <hi>Hero;</hi> unleſs it were done on purpoſe to diſparage <hi>Clelia,</hi> and with theſe indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities deſtroy the quality and reputation of an <hi>Heroine,</hi> which ſhe ſo well had me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited.</p>
            <p>Whereas our Author gives a hint of the <hi>Runick Characters,</hi> I might give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count here of the famous <hi>Edda,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the wonderful atchievments of <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and his Wife <hi>Frigga,</hi> (whoſe names we ſtill retain in our Wedneſday and Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day) with the reſt of our <hi>Gothiſh</hi> Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors: a Book which for antiquity might contend with <hi>Homer,</hi> and as fabulous as the beſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:107064:8"/>
            <p>And whereas in the controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Greeks</hi> and the <hi>Arabians</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Aeſop</hi> our Author ſeems to give the balance to the <hi>Greeks,</hi> I might eaſily turn the ſcales with the advantage to the <hi>Orientals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas he compute what time <hi>Rimes</hi> firſt obtained in <hi>Europe;</hi> I might examine whether or no <hi>Nero,</hi> who was a better Poet then <hi>Emperor,</hi> had any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them, and made then his diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and likewiſe whether they or the <hi>Meaſures</hi> and <hi>Cadences</hi> of the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Latins</hi> have the advantage, ſome affirming that <hi>Rime</hi> is trivial and childiſh, others aſſerting that <hi>Rime</hi> is more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, more ſweet, and more natural then the other; and though the other came firſt into the World, yet nature (like moſt Mothers) rather gives her bleſſing to the <hi>Cadet,</hi> then to the <hi>Firſt born.</hi> The ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral approbation of all Nations, and the <hi>Hebrews</hi> themſelves uſing <hi>Rime</hi> in whatever Poeſies they make at this day, all
<pb facs="tcp:107064:8"/>concur to the ſtrengthning of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>But I have already too long detained thee from what will give thee greater ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; ſhall therefore onely entreat that thou mayſt not impeach our Author for making <hi>Melkin</hi> and <hi>Thalieſſin</hi> Engliſh: ſeeing that Foreiners think themſelves not bound to take notice when this Iſle was called <hi>Albion,</hi> when <hi>Britain,</hi> when <hi>England;</hi> beſides that, writing in <hi>French,</hi> if <hi>he</hi> had call'd them <hi>Britains,</hi> they might have paſſed with ſome for <hi>French Britains,</hi> and thereby our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have loſt the honour of having given Birth to the firſt Romances in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:107064:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107064:9"/>
            <head>MONSIEUR HUET TO MONSIEUR <hi>de</hi> Ségrais.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur curioſity ſtands with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the deſire to know the Original of Romances is proper for you, who ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly underſtand the Art to make them; but the doubt is, whether it be ſo proper for me to undertake your ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>I have not Books, and my head at preſent is filled with matters of alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107064:10"/>another nature: And I know well how cumberſome and difficult this reſearch is; 'tis neither in <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence</hi> nor <hi>Spain</hi> (as many believe) that we may hope to find the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of this agreeable Amuſement; we muſt in queſt thereof travel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt Countries, and in the moſt latent Paths of Antiquity. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I will comply with your deſire; for as our ancient and ſtrict friendſhip gives you right to demand me all things, ſo it takes from me the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to deny you any thing.</p>
            <p>Heretofore under the name of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance were comprehended not onely thoſe which were writ in Proſe, but thoſe alſo which were writ in Verſe. <hi>Giraldi</hi> and <hi>Pigna</hi> his Diſciples in their Treatiſes <hi>De Romanzi</hi> ſcarce take notice of any others, and give the <hi>Boyardos</hi> and <hi>Arioſte</hi> for Models. But at this day the contrary uſage has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, and they which now are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107064:10"/>called Romances, are Fictions of Love-Adventures, writ in Proſe with Art, for the delight and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Readers.</p>
            <p>I ſay Fictions, to diſtinguiſh them from true Hiſtories; I add, of Love-Adventures, for that Love ought to be the principal ſubject of a Romance. They muſt be writ it Proſe, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Mode of the times. They muſt be writ with Art, and under certain rules; otherwiſe they will onely be a confuſed maſs without order or beauty.</p>
            <p>The chief end of a Romance, or (at leaſt) that which ought ſo to be, and which the Compoſer ought to propoſe to himſelf, is the Inſtruction of the Reader, to whom he muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways preſent Vertue crowned, and Vice puniſhed. But as the ſpirit of man naturally hates to be taught, and ſelf-love does ſpurn againſt Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, 'tis to be deceived by the blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhments
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107064:11"/>of pleaſure, and the ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Precepts to be ſweetn'd by the agreement of Examples; and thus our own faults may be amended while we condemn them in others.</p>
            <p>Thus the diverſion of the Reader, which a good Romancer ſeems chiefly to deſign, is but ſubordinate to his principal end, which is the Inſtruction of the mind, and correction of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: And Romances are more or leſs regular, according as they are more or leſs remote from this defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and end.</p>
            <p>'Tis onely of theſe I pretend to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain you, and I preſume your curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity reaches no further.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not therefore treat here of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances</hi> in Verſe, much leſs of <hi>Epick</hi> Poems; which beſides that they are in Verſe have moreover different eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials, which diſtinguiſh them from Romances, though otherwiſe there is a very great relation; and following
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107064:11"/>the maxime of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (who teaches that a Poet is more a Poet by the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions he invents then by the Verſe which he compoſes) Makers of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances</hi> may be rancked among the Poets. <hi>Petronius</hi> tells us that Poems are to move in a great circumference, by the Miniſtry of the Gods, and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions free and hardy, ſo that they may be taken rather for Oracles, thrown from a ſpirit full of fury, then for a faithfull and exact Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Romances are more ſimple, are not ſo lofty, nor have thoſe Figures in the invention and expreſſion.</p>
            <p>Poems have more of the marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, though always bounded within probability. Romances have more of the probable, though ſometimes they incline to the marvellous.</p>
            <p>Poems are more regular and more correct in the contrivance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive leſs of matter of Events and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſodes.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107064:12"/>
            <p>Romances are capable of more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe being not ſo elevate and full of Figures, they do not ſo much ſtretch the wit, and ſo ſuffer it to be furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a greater number of different <hi>Ideas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, Poems have for their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſome Military on Politick acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and treat not of Love but upon occaſion.</p>
            <p>Romances on the contrary have Love for their principal Theme, and meddle not with War or Politicks but by accident; I ſpeak of regular Romances: for the moſt part of the old <hi>French, Spaniſh,</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances have much more of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier then the Gallant in them.</p>
            <p>This made <hi>Giraldi</hi> believe that the name of Romance came from a Greek word, which ſignifies Force and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, becauſe theſe Books were made to ſet forth and vaunt the valour and proweſs of the <hi>Palladines;</hi> but <hi>Giraldi</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:107064:12"/>was miſtaken in this, as you ſhall ſee afterwards.</p>
            <p>Neither are theſe Hiſtories com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended here, which are obſerved to contain many falſehoods, ſuch as that of <hi>Herodotus,</hi> who (by the way) is not ſo guilty as many think. The Navigation of <hi>Hanno;</hi> the Life of <hi>Apollonius,</hi> writ by <hi>Philoſtratus,</hi> and many others.</p>
            <p>Theſe works are true in the mane, and falſe in ſome parts; Romances on the contrary are true in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and falſe in the groſs; thoſe contain truth mingled with ſome falſehood, theſe are falſehoods with ſome intermixture of truth. I would ſay that truth has the greater ſtroke, in Hiſtories, but that falſehood is predominant in the Romance, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that theſe may indeed be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether falſe, both in the parts and in the whole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> teaches us that Tragedy,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107064:13"/>the argument whereof is known and taken from Hiſtory, is the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, becauſe 'tis neerer veriſimility then that whoſe argument is new and mere invention; nevertheleſs he condemns not the later, his reaſon is for that notwithſtanding the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be drawn from Hiſtory, yet the greater number of the Spectators are ignorant of it, and it is new in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of them, and fails not however to give diverſion to all the World. The ſame may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid of Romances, with this diſtinction always, that a total Fiction of the argument is more allowable in Romances, where the Actors are but of indifferent Fortune, as in the <hi>Comick Romances,</hi> then in the <hi>Heroick Romances,</hi> where Princes and Conquerours are the Actors, and where the adventures are Memorable and Illuſtrious, becauſe 'tis in no wiſe probable that the great Tranſactions and Events lay hid to the World,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107064:13"/>and neglected by Hiſtorians and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability which is not always found in Hiſtory, is eſſential to a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.</p>
            <p>I exclude alſo from the number of Romances certain Hiſtories which in the groſs and in the detayl are mere invention, but invented onely for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of truth: ſuch are the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Originals of moſt Nations, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the moſt Barbarous; of which ſort are thoſe Hiſtories ſo groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forged by the Monk <hi>Annius Viter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benſis,</hi> which have merited the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or contempt of all the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>I put the ſame difference between Romances and theſe kinde of works, as betwixt thoſe who by an innocent artifice diſguiſe and go in Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade to divert themſelves, while they give diverſion to others. And Rogues who taking the name, and perſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as are dead or abſent, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107064:14"/>themſelves of their goods by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of ſome reſemblance.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I exclude Fables alſo from my Subject, for a Romance is the Fiction of things, which may but never have happened. Fables are Fictions of things, which never have nor ever can happen.</p>
            <p>After having agreed what works properly deſerve the name of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances,</hi> I aſſert that their invention is due to the <hi>Orientals,</hi> I mean to the <hi>Egyptians, Arabians, Perſians</hi> and <hi>Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi> You will avow the ſame with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, when I have ſhewn that moſt of the great Romancers of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity ſprung from theſe people. <hi>Clearcus,</hi> who made Books of Love, was of <hi>Cilicia</hi> a Province neer <hi>Syria. Iamblicus,</hi> who writ the Adventures of <hi>Rhodanes</hi> and <hi>Sinonis,</hi> was born of <hi>Syrian</hi> Parents, and educated at <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon. Heliodoras,</hi> Author of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of <hi>Theogenes</hi> and <hi>Chariclea,</hi> was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107064:14"/>of <hi>Emeſes</hi> a Town of <hi>Phoenicia. Lucian,</hi> who writ the <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> of <hi>Lucius</hi> into an Aſs, was of <hi>Samoſata,</hi> chief City of <hi>Comagena,</hi> a Province of <hi>Syria. Achilles Tatius,</hi> who taught us the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of <hi>Clitophon</hi> and <hi>Lencippe,</hi> was of <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Egypt.</hi> The Fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Hiſtory of <hi>Barlaam</hi> and <hi>Joſaphat</hi> was compoſed by St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Damas Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Syria. Damaſcius,</hi> who made four Books of Fictions, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incredible, as he Intitles them, but groſs and far remote from all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, was alſo (as <hi>Photius</hi> aſſures us) of <hi>Damas.</hi> The three <hi>Xenophons</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancers, which <hi>Suidas</hi> ſpeaks of, one was of <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> and another of them of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> an Iſle near that Countrey; ſo that this Countrey deſerves rather to be call'd the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Fables then <hi>Greece,</hi> whither they were onely Tranſplanted; but withall they found the Soil there ſo good and agreeable, that they have
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107064:15"/>admirably well taken Root.</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo hardly credible how all theſe People have a <hi>Genius</hi> ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed and addicted to Poetry, Invention and Fiction; all their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is Figures; they never expreſs themſelves but in Allegories; their Theologie and Philoſophie, but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally their Politicks and Morals, are all couched under Fables and Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boles.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>Hieroglyphicks</hi> of the <hi>Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians</hi> we may ſee to what point that Nation was Myſterious, every thing with them was expreſſed by Images, all in diſguiſe; their Religion was vayled; they never made diſcovery of it to the Prophane, but under the Maſque of Fables, and they never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ook off this Maſque, but for ſuch as they judged worthy to be imitated in their Myſteries. <hi>Herodotus</hi> ſaith that the <hi>Greeks</hi> had from them their <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thologick</hi> Theologie, and he tells ſome
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107064:15"/>ſtories, which he learned of the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Prieſts, the which (for all he is ſo credulous and fabulous himſelf) he relates onely as Tales; which Tales failed not to be agreeable, and tickle the curious wit of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (as <hi>Heleodorus</hi> teſtifies) deſirous to learn, and lovers of Novelty.</p>
            <p>And it was without doubt from theſe Prieſts that <hi>Pythagoras</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> in their Voyages to <hi>Egypt</hi> learned to transform their Philoſophie, and to hide it under the ſhadow of Myſteries and Diſguiſements.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Arabians</hi> conſult their Books, you will find nothing but Metaphores, drawn by the head and ſhoulders, ſimilitudes and fictions. Their <hi>Alcoran</hi> is of this ſort, <hi>Mahumet</hi> ſaith he made it ſo to the end it might be learned with leſs difficulty and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo eaſily be forgotten. They have tranſlated <hi>Eſops</hi> Fables into their Tongue, and ſome among them have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107064:16"/>compoſed the like. That <hi>Locman,</hi> ſo renowned throughout all the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> is no other but <hi>Aeſop;</hi> his Fables, which the <hi>Arabians</hi> have amaſſed together into a huge Volum, got him ſo great eſteem among them, that the <hi>Alcoran</hi> vaunteth his Wiſdom in one Chapter, which is therefore Intitled by the name of <hi>Locman.</hi> The lives of their Patriarchs, Prophets, and Apoſtles, are all fabulous. Nothing reliſhes ſo deliciouſly with them as Poeſie, which with them is the ordinary ſtudy of their beſt Wits. This inclination of theirs is not new, it poſseſsed them before <hi>Mahumet,</hi> and they have Poems of thoſe times. <hi>Aerpennius</hi> affirms, that all the World beſide put together have not had ſo many Poets as ſingle <hi>Arabia.</hi> They reckon ſixty which are among them as it were Princes of Poeſie, and which have great Troops of Poets under them. The beſt have treated of Love in their <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:107064:16"/>and ſome of their Books on this Subject have paſsed into the <hi>Weſt.</hi> Many of their <hi>Caliphs</hi> have not thought Poeſie unworthy of their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication. <hi>Abdalla</hi> (one amongſt them) ſignalized himſelf upon this occaſion, and made a Book of Similitudes, as <hi>Elmacin</hi> reports.</p>
            <p>'Tis from the <hi>Arabians</hi> (in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) that we receive the art of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; and I ſee much of probability that the <hi>Leonine</hi> Verſes have been made after their example; for it does not at all appear that rimes had courſe in <hi>Europe,</hi> before the entrance of <hi>Taric</hi> and <hi>Muza</hi> into <hi>Spain;</hi> whereas great quantity might be obſerved in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Ages; though otherwiſe I could eaſily make it appear, that Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Rime were not altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the Ancient <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Perſians</hi> have not at all yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Arabians</hi> in the art of Lying agreeably; for notwithſtanding Lies
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107064:17"/>were otherwiſe moſt odious to them in converſation, and they forbid their Children nothing with ſo great ſeverity; nevertheleſs in their Books and Commerce of letters, theſe pleaſed them infinitely if Fictions are to be called Lies. To be convinced of this one ſhall onely read the fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Adventures of their Law-giver <hi>Zoroaſter. Strabo</hi> ſaith that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters among them give their Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Moral Precepts, wrapt up in Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: he tells us in another place that much credit is not to be given to the Ancient Hiſtories of the <hi>Perſians, Medes,</hi> and <hi>Syrians,</hi> by reaſon of the inclination their Writers had to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late untruths for theſe, ſeeing that they who made profeſſion of writing Fables were in eſteem, were perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that people would take pleaſure to read Fables and forged Relations, written after the manner of Hiſtories. The Fables of <hi>Aeſop</hi> are ſo much to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107064:17"/>their guſt, that they appropriate the Author: he is the ſame <hi>Locman</hi> of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> whom I mentioned before, who is ſo renowned among all the people of the <hi>Levant,</hi> that they will needs rob <hi>Phrygia</hi> of the honour of his birth, and attribute it to themſelves; for the <hi>Arabians</hi> ſay he was of the Race of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> ſay he was an <hi>Arabian Negro,</hi> and lived in the Town of <hi>Caſuvin,</hi> which was the <hi>Arſacia</hi> of the Ancients. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers on the contrary ſeeing that his life writ by <hi>Mirkond</hi> has much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance with that of <hi>Aeſop,</hi> which <hi>Maximus Planudes</hi> has left us; and having obſerved that as Angels give Wiſdom to <hi>Locman</hi> in <hi>Mirkond,</hi> ſo <hi>Mercury</hi> beſtows the Fable upon <hi>Aeſop</hi> in <hi>Philoſtratus.</hi> They are perſwaded that the <hi>Greeks</hi> have ſtoln <hi>Locman</hi> from the <hi>Orientals,</hi> and made thereof their <hi>Aeſop;</hi> but I muſt not here diſcuſs this controverſie. I ſhall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107064:18"/>onely put you in mind by the way to remember what is ſaid by <hi>ſtrabo;</hi> that the Hiſtories of the people of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> are ſtuft with Lies, and are in no wiſe faithful or exact; and that it is moſt probable they have been Fabulous in ſpeaking of the Author and Original of Fables, as well as in all the reſt; and that the <hi>Greeks</hi> are more diligent, and of better credit, both in their Chronology and Hiſtory; and that the conformity of <hi>Mirkonds Locman</hi> with the <hi>Aeſop</hi> of <hi>Planudes</hi> and <hi>Philoſtratus,</hi> does no more prove that <hi>Aeſop</hi> is <hi>Loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> then it proves that <hi>Locman</hi> is <hi>Aeſop.</hi> The <hi>Perſians</hi> have ſirnamed <hi>Locman</hi> the <hi>Sage,</hi> for that <hi>Aeſop</hi> was in effect ranckt among the number of the Sages. They ſay he was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly knowing in Medicine, that he found out admirable Secrets, and among the reſt that of reviving the Dead.</p>
            <p>They have ſo well gloſſed, para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſed,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107064:18"/>and augmented his Fables, that they (as the <hi>Arabians</hi>) have made thereof a very great Volum, a Copy whereof is to be ſeen in the <hi>Vatican;</hi> his Reputation has reatched even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Egypt</hi> and into <hi>Nubia,</hi> where his Name and Wiſdom are in great ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. The <hi>Modern</hi> Turks have no leſs eſteem for him, and believe with <hi>Mirkond</hi> that he lived in <hi>Davids</hi> time, wherein (if in truth it be <hi>Aeſop,</hi> and that we may believe the <hi>Greek</hi> Chronologie) they are miſtaken but about the matter of 450 years, which for the Turks is very well computed, for they rarely hit ſo neer in their computation. This would accord better with <hi>Heſiod,</hi> who was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and to whom is due (according to the report of <hi>Quintilian</hi>) the glory of the firſt inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Fables, which is attributed to <hi>Aeſop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are no Poets that equal the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107064:19"/>
               <hi>Perſians</hi> in the licence they give themſelves to Lye: in the lives of their Saints, and about the Original of their Religion, and in their Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, they have ſo disfigured thoſe, the truth whereof we know by the relations of the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> that they are not to be known again; and even degenerating from that laudable averſion they hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had againſt thoſe who ſerved themſelves with a lye for their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, they now account it an honour. They are paſſionately in love with Poeſie; it is the diverſion both of the Princes and People, and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal at a <hi>Begale</hi> were wanting, if no Poetry were there. Their works of Galantry, and Love-ſtories have been famous, and diſcover the Romancing <hi>Genius</hi> of this Nation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Indians</hi> alſo (Neighbours of the <hi>Perſians</hi>) had like them a ſtrong incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to fabulous inventions. <hi>Sanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:107064:19"/>the <hi>Indian</hi> compoſed a Book of Paraboles, which was Tranſlated by the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and which at this day is to be found in the Libraries of the curious. Father <hi>Pouſſin</hi> the Jeſuit has joyned to his <hi>Pachymeron,</hi> which he lately Printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> a Dialogue between <hi>Abſolom</hi> King of the <hi>Indies</hi> and a <hi>Gymnoſophiſt,</hi> upon divers que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of Morality, wherein this Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher never expreſſes himſelf but by Paraboles and Fables, after the manner of <hi>Aeſop.</hi> The Preface imports that this Book was made by the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt and moſt knowing Men of the Nation, and that it was carefully kept in the Treaſury of the Charters of the Realm; that <hi>Perzoez,</hi> Phyſician of <hi>Choſroez</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> Tranſlated it out of <hi>Indian</hi> into <hi>Perſian;</hi> ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from <hi>Perſian</hi> into <hi>Arabian,</hi> and <hi>Simeon Sethi</hi> from <hi>Arabian</hi> into <hi>Greek.</hi> This Book is ſo little different from the Apologues, which bear the name
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107064:20"/>of the <hi>Indian Pilpay,</hi> and which were ſeen in <hi>French</hi> ſome few years ſince, that there is no doubt but that it was either the Original or the Copy; for 'tis ſaid that this <hi>Pilpay</hi> was a <hi>Brachman</hi> who had ſhare in the grand affairs of State and Government of the <hi>Indies</hi> under King <hi>Dabchelin,</hi> that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes all his Politicks and Morals within this Book, which was preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Kings of the <hi>Indies</hi> as a Treaſure of Wiſdom and Learning: that the reputation of this Book be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried ſo far as to <hi>Nonchirevon</hi> King of <hi>Perſia;</hi> he procured a Copy thereof by the means of his Phyſician, who Tranſlated it into <hi>Perſian,</hi> that <hi>Calife Abuiafar Almanzor</hi> cauſed it to be Tranſlated from <hi>Perſian</hi> into <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian,</hi> and another out of <hi>Arabian</hi> into <hi>Perſian;</hi> and that after all theſe <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> tranſlations, a new one was made different from all the former, and from this came the <hi>French</hi> tranſlation.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107064:20"/>Certainly whoever ſhall read the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the pretended Patriarchs of the <hi>Indians Erammon</hi> and <hi>Bremaw,</hi> of their Poſterity and Propagation, ſhall need no other proof of the love this people have for Fables. I therefore readily believe that when <hi>Horace</hi> gave the Epithete of Fabulous to the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Hydappes,</hi> which has its Source in <hi>Perſia,</hi> and finiſhes its courſe in the <hi>Indies;</hi> his thought and meaning was that it begins and end its courſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong people very much addicted to Fiction and Diſguiſements.</p>
            <p>Theſe Fictions and Paraboles which you have ſeen make up the Prophane learning of the Nations before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, have in <hi>Syria</hi> been Sanctified; the Sacred Authors complying with the humour of the <hi>Jews,</hi> made uſe thereof to expreſs the inſpirations they received from Heaven. The Holy Scripture is altogether Myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Allegorical, and Aenigmatical.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107064:21"/>The <hi>Talmudiſts</hi> believed that the Book of <hi>Job</hi> is no other but a parable of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> invention: this Book, that of <hi>Davia,</hi> the <hi>Proverbs, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes,</hi> the <hi>Canticles,</hi> and all other Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Songs, are Poetical works abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Figures, which would ſeem bold and violent in our Writings; and which are ordinary in thoſe of that Nation. The Book of <hi>Proverbs</hi> is otherwiſe called the <hi>Paraboles;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Proverbs</hi> of this ſort, according to the definition of <hi>Quintilian,</hi> are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhort Fictions, or Parables expreſt in little.</p>
            <p>The Book of <hi>Canticles</hi> is a kind of Dramatick Poem, where the paſſionat ſentiments of the Bridegroom and Spouſe are expreſt after a manner ſo tender and touching, that we ſhould be charmed thereby; if theſe expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and figures had ſome little more of conformity with our <hi>Genius,</hi> or that we could deveſt our ſelves of that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107064:21"/>unjuſt preoccupation, which makes us diſlike all that is any little remote from our uſage, in which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn our ſelves without perceiving it; ſince that our lightneſs never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits us to perſevere long in the ſame cuſtomes.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour himſelf ſcarce ever gave any precepts to the <hi>Jews,</hi> but under the veil of Paraboles. The <hi>Talmud</hi> contains a Million of Fables, every one more impertinent then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: many of the <hi>Rabbins</hi> have after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards explained, reconciled, and amaſſed them together in their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular works; and beſides this have compoſed ſeveral Poeſies, Proverbs, and Apologues.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cypriots</hi> and <hi>Cilicians</hi> have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented certain Fables, which did bear the name of theſe People; and the habit which the <hi>Cilicians</hi> in particular had of Lying, has been noted by one of the Ancienteſt Proverbs, which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107064:22"/>has been currant in <hi>Greece.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Fables have been in ſuch vogue all over theſe Countries, that amongſt the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> and <hi>Arabians</hi> (according to the teſtimony of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi>) there were certain perſons, whoſe ſole profeſſion was to explain Fables; and theſe men lived ſo regularly, that they lived far longer then other People.</p>
            <p>But it is not ſufficient to have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the Source of Romances; we muſt ſee by what Chanels they have been conveyed to, and ſpread over <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Italy:</hi> and whether they have paſſed from thence to us, or that we have them from elſewhere. The <hi>Ionians,</hi> a people of <hi>Aſia Minor,</hi> being raiſed to a great Power, and having acquired vaſt Riches, were plunged in Luxurie and Voluptuouſneſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeperable companions of plenty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyrus</hi> having ſubdued them, by the taking of <hi>Craeſus,</hi> and all <hi>Aſia Minor</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:107064:22"/>being with them fallen under the power of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> they received their manners with their Laws; and mixing their Debauches with thoſe their own inclination had before car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried them to; they became the moſt Voluptuous people in the World: they refined upon the pleaſures of the Table, they made the addition of Flowers and Perfumes, they found out new Ornaments for their Houſes; the fineſt Wools, and the faireſt Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtries of the World came from them; they were Authors of the Laſcivious Dance called the <hi>Ionick;</hi> and they became ſo remarkable for effeminateneſs, that it paſt into a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb: but amongſt theſe <hi>Mileſians</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed all in the ſcience of pleaſures, and were moſt ingenious in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacies: theſe were the firſt who taught the <hi>Perſians</hi> the Art of making Romances, and travelled therein ſo happily, that the <hi>Mileſian</hi> Fables, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107064:23"/>is to ſay their Romances, full of Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories and diſſolute Relations, were in the higheſt reputation: 'tis very likely that Romances were innocent, till they fell into their hands; and only contained ſingular and memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble adventures: that theſe firſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted them, and ſtuft them with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcivions narrations and affairs of love. Time has conſumed all theſe works; it has indeed preſerved the name of <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> the moſt famous of their Romancers, who writ ſeveral Books of thoſe called <hi>Mileſian</hi> Fables. I find that one <hi>Dioniſins</hi> a <hi>Mileſian,</hi> who liv'd under the firſt <hi>Darius,</hi> writ fabulous Hiſtories, but not being certain whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this was not onely a compilation of Ancient Fables, and not ſeeing ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient foundation, to believe that theſe were of thoſe, properly called <hi>Mileſian</hi> Fables, I do not number him amongſt the makers of Romances.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Ionians</hi> who came from <hi>Attica</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:107064:23"/>and <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> mindful of their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, maintained a great correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the <hi>Greeks.</hi> They ſent their children reciprocally for breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that they might be acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with each others manners; by this ſo frequent commerce, <hi>Greece,</hi> which of it ſelf had inclination enough for Fables, learned readily of the <hi>Ionians</hi> the art of compoſing Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, and did cultivate it with ſucceſs; but to avoid confuſion, I ſhall eſſay, according to the order of time to give account of thoſe <hi>Greek</hi> Writers, who have been famous in this art.</p>
            <p>I find none before <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> which perſwaded me that the <hi>Romantick</hi> Science made no conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able progreſs among the <hi>Greeks,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had it from the <hi>Perſians</hi> themſelves when they ſubdued them, and run it to its Source. <hi>Clearcus</hi> of <hi>Soli,</hi> a Town of <hi>Cilicia,</hi> who lived
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107064:24"/>in <hi>Alexanders</hi> time, and was with him a Diſciple of <hi>Ariſtotles,</hi> is the firſt I find to have writ Books of Love; though I do not well know whether theſe were not a Collection onely of ſeveral Love-paſſages, drawn from Hiſtory or vulgar Fable, like that which <hi>Parthenius</hi> afterwards made under <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> which is yet extant. That which cauſeth this ſuſpition, is a little ſtory cited by <hi>Atheneus</hi> out of him, wherein are reckoned ſeveral tokens of love and eſteem, which <hi>Gyges</hi> King of <hi>Lydia</hi> gave to a Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan his Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonius Diogenes</hi> according to the conjecture of <hi>Photius</hi> lived ſome little time after <hi>Alexander,</hi> and in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Homers Odyſſeis,</hi> and the hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Voyages of <hi>Uliſſes,</hi> made a true Romance of the Voyages and Amours of <hi>Dinias</hi> and <hi>Dercyllis.</hi> This Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, though very faulty in many things, and filled with fooleries and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107064:24"/>relations improbable, and ſcarce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable even in a Poet, may not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding be called regular. <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> has an abſtract thereof in his <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliotheca,</hi> and ſaith he believes it to be the ſource of that which <hi>Lucian, Lucius, Iamblicus, Achilles Tatius, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liodorus,</hi> and <hi>Damaſcius</hi> have writ in this kind; however, he adds in the ſame place, that <hi>Antonius Diogenes</hi> makes mention of one <hi>Antiphanes</hi> more ancient then himſelf, who (he ſaith) writ a Book of wonderful Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, like his; ſo that he may as well be thought to have given the <hi>Idaea</hi> and matter to theſe Romances which he names, as <hi>Antonius Diogenes.</hi> I ſuppoſe he muſt be underſtood to ſpeak of <hi>Antiphanes</hi> the Comick Poet, who, the Geographer <hi>Stephanus</hi> and others ſay, made a Book of incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble relations and ridiculous. He was of <hi>Berge</hi> a Town of <hi>Thrace,</hi> but 'tis not known of what Countrey <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Diogenes</hi> was.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:107064:25"/>
            <p>I cannot tell preciſely in what time <hi>Ariſtides</hi> of <hi>Miletus</hi> lived, whom I ſpoke of before; what we may be confident of is, that he lieved before the Wars of <hi>Marius</hi> and <hi>Sylla,</hi> for <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenna</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtorian of that time tranſlated his <hi>Mileſian</hi> Fables: this work was full of obſcenities, and thereby gave great delight and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſo that the <hi>Surenas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or Lieutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the <hi>Parthian</hi> Eſtate, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated the <hi>Roman</hi> Army under <hi>Craſſus</hi> his Command, having found theſe among the Baggage of <hi>Roſcius,</hi> took occaſion thereupon before the Senate of <hi>Seleucia,</hi> to inſult over and rail at the weakneſs and effeminate diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Romans,</hi> who even during the War could not be without ſuch like diverſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucius</hi> of <hi>Pairas, Lucian</hi> of <hi>Samoſata,</hi> and <hi>Iamblicus</hi> were all well nigh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries, and lived under <hi>Antoninus</hi> and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107064:25"/>
               <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> the firſt of theſe is not to be accounted among Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, for he onely made a collection of Metamorphoſes, and the Magical Transforming of Men into Beaſts, and of Beaſts into Men, dealing <hi>bona fide,</hi> and believing every thing that he writ. But <hi>Lucian</hi> more wiſe and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning then he, relates ſome part of his Hiſtory to mock and make ſport therewith, according to his cuſtom, in the Book which he Intitled <hi>Lucius his Aſs,</hi> to intimate that that Fiction was taken from him. This in effect is an Abbridgement of the two firſt Books of <hi>Lucius</hi> his Metamorphoſes, and this fragment lets us ſee that <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> had reaſon to complain of the ſmuttineſs ſo frequent in him. This ſo ingenious and renowned <hi>Aſs,</hi> whoſe Hiſtory theſe Authors writ, was much akin to another of like worth and merit, whereof elſewhere the ſame <hi>Photius</hi> ſpeaks after <hi>Damaſcius;</hi> This
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:107064:26"/>Aſs (ſaith he) was the Chattel of a certain <hi>Grammarian</hi> named <hi>Ammonius,</hi> and was indued with ſuch a gentle ſpirit, and 2o born to be polite and capable of fine things, that it would gladly even leave Meat and Drink, to hear Verſes repeated, and would be ſenſibly touched and taken with the graces and beauties of the Poetry. The <hi>Brancaleon</hi> is doubtleſs a Copy of this <hi>Aſs</hi> of <hi>Lucians,</hi> or of that of <hi>Apu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leus;</hi> this is an <hi>Italian</hi> Fiction very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſing and full of Wit. <hi>Lucian</hi> beſides his <hi>Lucius</hi> made two Books of wild and ridiculous Hiſtories, and which he declared to be ſuch, proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing withall that thoſe things never have, nor ever can come to paſs; ſome ſeeing theſe Books joyned to that wherein he gives directions for the writing a Hiſtory well, have been perſwaded that he intended this for an example of what he had taught, but he declares at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:107064:26"/>of the Book, that he had not any further deſign in it, ſave only to mock at ſo many Poets, Hiſtorians, and even Philoſophers themſelves, who with impunity delivered Fables for truths, and writ ſuch falſe relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Forein Countries, as <hi>Cteſias</hi> and <hi>Iambulus</hi> had done. If then it be true, as <hi>Photius</hi> aſſures us, that the Romance of <hi>Antonius Diogenes</hi> has been the Source of theſe two Books of <hi>Lucian;</hi> 'tis to be underſtood that <hi>Lucian</hi> took occaſion from this Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, as alſo from the Fabulous Hiſtories of <hi>Cieſias</hi> and <hi>Iambulus,</hi> to write his, and thereby make their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and impertinence appear.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time <hi>Iamblious</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed his <hi>Babylonicks,</hi> for ſo he called his Romance, in which he far excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all thoſe who went before, for if one may judge of it by the abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which <hi>Photius</hi> has left us, his deſign comprehends but one action,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107064:27"/>dreſſed with all convenient Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, accornpanied with <hi>Epiſodes</hi> ariſing from the principal matter; Veriſimility is obſerved moſt exactly, the Adventures are mixed with a World of Variety and without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, Art onely is wanting in the contrivance of his Plot; he has groſly followed the order of time, and has not at his firſt Launching plundged the Reader, as he might have done, into the middle of his ſubject after the example <hi>Homer</hi> gives us in his <hi>Odyſſis.</hi> Time has been favourable to this Piece, and it is to be ſeen in the Library of the <hi>Eſcurial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heliodorus</hi> has ſurpaſſed him in the diſpoſition of his Subject, as in all the reſt. Hitherto the World had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen any thing better deſigned, and more compleat among Romances, then the Adventures of <hi>Theagenes</hi> and <hi>Chariclea,</hi> nothing can be more chaſte then their Loves. Whereby may
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:107064:27"/>appear (beſides the Chriſtian Religion, whereof the Author made profeſſion) that his own nature had given him ſuch an air of Vertue, as ſhines throughout all his work; in which not onely <hi>Iamblicus,</hi> but even almoſt all the reſt are much his Inferiours; beſides his Merit advanced him to the Dignity of an Epiſcopal Sea, he was Biſhop of <hi>Tricca</hi> a City of <hi>Theſſalie;</hi> and <hi>Socrates</hi> reports that he intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced within that Province the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of depoſing ſuch of the Clergy, as abſtained not from thoſe Women they had Eſpouſed before they were ordained Prieſts. All which makes me much ſuſpect what <hi>Nicophorus</hi> a cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous Writer of little judgement or fidelity relates, that a Provincial Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node underſtanding what danger the reading of this Romance, which was authoriſed by the dignity of its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, made the young people fall into; and having propoſed to him this alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:107064:28"/>either to conſent that his Book ſhould be burned, or elſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign his Biſhoprick, he made choice of the latter; for the reſt I cannot but exceedingly wonder that a Learned Man of theſe times ſhould doubt whether this was the Book of <hi>Heliodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tricca</hi> or no, after ſo evident Teſtimony of <hi>Socrates, Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and <hi>Nicephorua.</hi> Some have been of opinion that he lived about the end of the twelft Age, confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with <hi>Heliodorus</hi> the <hi>Arabian,</hi> whoſe life <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> has writ among thoſe of the other <hi>Sophiſts.</hi> But it is known that he was contemporary of <hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Honoriu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> we alſo ſee that in the Catalogue which <hi>Photius</hi> made of the Romancers, who he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved had imitated <hi>Antonius Diogenes,</hi> where he names them according to the order of time, he has placed <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioderus</hi> after <hi>Iamblicus,</hi> and before <hi>Damaſcius,</hi> who lived in the time
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:107064:28"/>of the Emperous <hi>Juſtinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this account <hi>Achilles Tatius,</hi> who made a regular Romance of the Amours of <hi>Clitophon</hi> and <hi>Leucippe,</hi> ſhould have preceded, for I find nothing elſe whereon to ground my conjecture of his Age, others think him more recent by his ſtyle, but however he is not in any wiſe to be compared with <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> neither in the regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his manners, nor in the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of events, nor in the Artifice in unravelling his Plots; his ſtile (in my mind) is to be preferr'd to that of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liodorus,</hi> he is more ſimple and natural, but <hi>Heliodorus</hi> more forced: finally, ſome ſay that he was a Chriſtian and Biſhop too; 'tis ſtrange that the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenity of his Book ſhould be ſo eaſily forgot, and more then this that the Emperour <hi>Leon</hi> ſurnamed the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, has commended the Modeſty thereof in an <hi>Epigram,</hi> which is yet extant, and not onely permitted, but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:107064:29"/>counſelled the reading of it from one end to the other; to thoſe who profeſs the love of Chaſtity.</p>
            <p>Poſſibly I place here too raſhly that <hi>Athenagoras,</hi> under whoſe name there goes a Romance, the Title whereof is, <hi>of true and perfect Love;</hi> this Book has not appeared abroad but onely in <hi>French</hi> of <hi>Fumee</hi>'s tranſlation, who tells us in the Preface that he had the <hi>Greek</hi> Origina from Mr. <hi>du Lamane,</hi> Prothonotary of Mr. the Cardinal <hi>d'Armagnac,</hi> and that he never ſaw it elſewhere. I almoſt dare add, that never any perſon ſaw it ſince, for his name was never mentioned (that I know of) in the Catalogues of any Libraries; and if at this day it have any being, 'tis certainly buried among the duſt, in the Cloſet of 2ome Illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate perſon, who poſſeſſes this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and knows not of it; or elſe 'tis in the hands of the envious, who might gratifie the publick therewith
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:107064:29"/>but will not; the Tranſlator ſaith further, that he believes this to be the Production of that famous <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoras,</hi> who writ the Apology for Chriſtian Religion, in the manner of a Legation, addreſſed to the Emperours <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> and <hi>Commodus,</hi> and a Treatiſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. The chief ground of his opinion is the ſtyle which he finds conformable to that of his works, and whereof he might well enough judge, having the Originals in his power. And finally he takes this for a true Hiſtory, not underſtanding the art of Romances. For my part though I cannot pronounce thereof with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, not having ſeen the <hi>Greek</hi> Original, nevertheleſs by reading the Tranſlation I ſhall not ſtick to affirm that he does not without ſome reaſon attribute it to <hi>Athenagoras</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Apology, the reaſons are, that the Apologiſt was a Chriſtian,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:107064:30"/>and this ſpeaks of Divinity, after a manner which is inconſiſtent with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but a Chriſtian, as when he makes the Prieſts of <hi>Hammon</hi> ſay, <q>That there is but one God, and that every Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion deſirous to repreſent his eſſence to the ſimple, had invented divers I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, all which expreſt but the ſame thing; that their true ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being loſt with the times, the Vulgar believed that there were ſo many Gods as they ſaw Images, and idolatry ſprung from thence, that <hi>Bacchus</hi> when he built the Temple of <hi>Hammon,</hi> placed in it no other I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage ſave onely that of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as there is but one Heaven, which contains but one World, ſo in this World there is but one God, who is communicated in Spirit. He makes thus much and more be ſaid by certain <hi>Egyptian</hi> Merchants, to wit, that the Gods of the Fable denoted the different actions of this
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:107064:30"/>Soveraign, and one only Divinity, who is without beginning and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, and whom he calls obſcure and dark, for that he is Inviſible and Incomprehenſible.</q> Moreover the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of the Prieſts and Merchants upon the Divine Eſſence, very much reſemble thoſe of <hi>Athenagor as</hi> in his <hi>Legation;</hi> the Apologiſt was a Prieſt of <hi>Athens,</hi> this was on <hi>Athenean</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, both ſeem Men of ſenſe and great learning, and well read in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity.</p>
            <p>But on the other ſide many things may make us ſuſpect, not onely that this is not <hi>Athenagoras</hi> the Chriſtian, but alſo that the Book it ſelf is a meer forgery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Photius</hi> giving an exact account of thoſe who had been makers of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances before his time, takes no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of him at all; no body ever ſaw a Copy of this Romance in any Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary, and that which the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:107064:31"/>made uſe of never appeared ſince. Beſides he repreſents the Habitation, Life, and Conduct of the Prieſts and <hi>Religious</hi> of <hi>Hammon,</hi> ſo very like the Convents and the Government of our Monks and <hi>Religious,</hi> that it ill accords with what Hiſtory informs us of the time when the Monaſtick life began, and when it arrived to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>What among ſo much obſcurity ſeems to me moſt probable is, that this is an ancient work, but later then the Apology.</p>
            <p>For I find ſuch a profound know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge both in things, of Nature and of Art, ſo great acquaintance with the Annals of times paſt, ſo many curious remarks not taken from the Ancient Authors, which are left us, but which relate to and explain them, ſo much of the <hi>Greek</hi> Phraſe, which one may diſcover thorow the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, and over all a certain Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:107064:31"/>of Antiquity, which cannot be counterfeited; ſo that I cannot be perſwaded that it is any production of <hi>Fumee</hi>'s, whoſe Learning was but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, or that the moſt able and ingenious perſon in thoſe days could deviſe any thing like it; if <hi>Photius</hi> have not mentioned him. How many other great and famous Authors have eſcaped his cogniſance, or his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence? and if in our days onely one Copy was found, which peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſince loſt, how many other excellent works have undergone the ſame deſtiny? if this gives you not ſatisfaction, but you will oblige me to puſh further my conjectures, and eſſay to find out preciſely the time he lived in, I have nothing to ſupport my opinion, ſave one paſsage in the Preface of his Romance, where he complains of the fatal blow, which his Countrey <hi>Athens</hi> was about to receive in the univerſal deſolation of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:107064:32"/>
               <hi>Greece,</hi> which cannot be underſtood, but of the <hi>Scythians</hi> irruption into <hi>Greece,</hi> which happened under the Empire of <hi>Gallienus,</hi> or elſe of that of <hi>Alaric</hi> King of the <hi>Goths,</hi> which fell out in the times of <hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius,</hi> for <hi>Athens</hi> was not ſacked ſince <hi>Sylla</hi>'s time, till the Invaſion of the <hi>Scythians,</hi> which was about 350. years after, and that of the <hi>Goths</hi> was about 700 years after, but I ſee more reaſon to apply the words of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to the Conqueſt of <hi>Alaric,</hi> then to that of the <hi>Scythians,</hi> for that the <hi>Scythians</hi> were readily chaced from <hi>Athens</hi> ere they had done much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, but the <hi>Goths</hi> treated them more rudely, and left there the ſad marques of their barbarous cruelty. <hi>Syneſius</hi> who lived at that time, ſpeaks of them in the ſame terms with our Author, and with him regrets to ſee learning, &amp; the liberal ſciences wract by the Barbarians, in the very place
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:107064:32"/>of their Birth and Seat of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; but howſoever, this work of <hi>Athenagoras</hi> is invented with wit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted with Art, Sententious, and full of excellent moral Precepts, the events agreeing with veriſimility, the <hi>Epiſodes</hi> drawn from the ſubject, the Characters clear and diſtinct, <hi>Decorum</hi> obſerved exactly all throughout, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing low, nothing forced, or like the Pedant ſtile of the <hi>Sophiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The argument is double, that which made one of the great Beauties of the ancient Comedy, for beſides the Adventures of <hi>Theogenes</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridea;</hi> he relates likewiſe thoſe of <hi>Pherecydes</hi> and <hi>Melangenia,</hi> whereby may appear the miſtake of <hi>Giraldi,</hi> who believed that the multiplying of actions was the invention of the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians;</hi> the <hi>Greeks</hi> and our old <hi>French</hi> have practiſed this before the <hi>Italians,</hi> the <hi>Greeks</hi> with dependance and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination to one principal action
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:107064:33"/>following the rules of an Heroick Poem, as <hi>Athenagoras</hi> has done, and <hi>Heliodorus</hi> too, though not ſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, but our old <hi>French</hi> have mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed them without any order, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion, or art; theſe are them whom the <hi>Italians</hi> have imitated, taking from them their Romances and their faults together; and this is an error in <hi>Giraldi</hi> worſe then the former, that he would endeavour to commend this fault, and make thereof a vertue, if it be true, which himſelf acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges that a Romance ſhould reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a perfect Body, and conſiſt of many different parts and proprotions, all under one head; it follows then that the principal action which is as it were, the head of a Romance ſhould onely be one, and illuſtrious above the reſt; and that the ſubordinate actions, which are as it were mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, ought to have relation to this head, yield to it in dignity and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:107064:33"/>adorn, ſuſtain and attend it with dependance; otherwiſe it would be a Body with many Heads, monſtrous and deformed. The example of <hi>Ovid</hi> alledged in his favour, and that of other Cyclick Poets, which he might alſo cite, does not juſtifie him in the leaſt, for the Metamorphoſes of the ancient Fable, which <hi>Ovid</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to himſelf to amaſs into one Poem, and thoſe of the <hi>Cyclick</hi> Poets conſiſting all of actions, which have no dependance on or relation to one another, and being all well nigh of equal beauty and eminence, it was altogether as impoſſible to make thereof one regular Body, as to build one complete Structure with Sand on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The applauſe which the faulty Romances of his Nation have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and which he relles ſo much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, does yet juſtifie him leſs, one muſt not judge of a piece by the number, but by the ſufficiency of the approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:107064:34"/>every one aſſume to themſelves the licence to judge and cenſure Poeſie and Romance; the ſumptuous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces and the common Streets are made Tribunals, where the merits of greateſt works is Soveraignly decided. There every one ſhoots his bolt, and preſumes boldly to ſet the value of an <hi>Epick</hi> Poem upon the reading of a compariſon or a deſcription: and one Verſe ſomewhat harſh, ſuch as the place and matter ſometimes requires, may there ruine the reputation of all, one happy thought or tender ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment makes there the fortune of a Romance, and one expreſſion a little forc't, or one ſuperannuated word deſtroys it; but they who compoſe them will in no wiſe ſubmit to theſe deciſions, but like the Comedian in <hi>Horace,</hi> who being hiſſed from the Stage by the people, contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the approbation of the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valliers. Theſe are content that they
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:107064:34"/>pleaſe the niceſt and moſt able Judges, who have other kind of Laws to judge by; and theſe Laws are known to ſo very few, that as I often have ſaid before, a good Judge is as rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be met withall as a good Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancer, or a good Poet: and that in the ſmall number of thoſe who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and can judge of Proſe, hardly one can be found who underſtands Poeſie, or who is ſenſible and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends that Poeſie and Proſe are things altogether different. Theſe Criticks, whoſe Sentence is the certain rule to value Poems and Romances by, did avow to <hi>Giraldi,</hi> that the <hi>Italian</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances have many very pretty things in them, and deſerve many other commendations, but not that of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity, contrivance, nor juſteſs of deſign. I return to the Romance of <hi>Athenagoras,</hi> where the diſcovery of the plot, though without machine, is leſs happy then the reſt; it goes not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:107064:35"/>of ſmartly enough, it preſents it ſelf before the paſſion and impatience of the Reader be ſufficiently warmed, and is made with too much repetition; but his greateſt fault is the unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able oſtentation, wherewith he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plays his skill in Architecture, what he writes thereof might be admirable elſewhere, but is vicious, and out of of its place where he puts it. <hi>Ne doe anco il Poeta,</hi> ſaith Giraldi, <hi>nel deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere le Fabrichu, volerſi moſtrare in guiſa Architettore, che deſcrivendo trop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po minutamente le coſe a tale arte appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinenti, laſci quello che conviene al Poeta; alla quaſe coſa egli doe ſoura ogni coſa mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare, ſe cerca loda oltre che queſte deſcrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni di coſe mechaniche recano con loro vilta, &amp; ſono <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontane, &amp; dall uſo, &amp; dal grande dell Heroico.</hi> 
               <q>A Poet ought not in deſcribing a Fabrick to ſhew himſelf an Architect; for in deſcribing too minutely the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars appertaining to ſuch an art,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:107064:35"/>he leaves what is properly a Poets work, which it concerns him prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to look to, if he expect commendation; beſides, that ſuch mechanick deſcriptions debaſe the work, are too mean and far below, the grandeur and magnificence of an Heroick Poem.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He has taken many things from <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> or <hi>Heliodorus</hi> from him; for as I believe them contemporaries, I know not to whether is due the glory of the invention. The names and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of <hi>Theogenes</hi> and <hi>Charidea</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble thoſe of <hi>Theagenes</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riclea. Theogenes</hi> and <hi>Charidea</hi> ſee and fall in love with each other at a Feaſt of <hi>Minerva;</hi> as <hi>Theagenes</hi> and <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clea</hi> at a Feaſt of <hi>Apollo. Athenagoras</hi> makes one <hi>Harondates</hi> Governour of the lower <hi>Egypt. Heliodorus</hi> makes <hi>Oroondates</hi> Governour of <hi>Egypt. Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoras</hi> feigns <hi>Theogenes</hi> ready to be Sacrificed by the <hi>Scythians. Heliodorus</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:107064:36"/>makes <hi>Theagenes</hi> ready to be Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the <hi>Aethiopians,</hi> and <hi>Athenago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> like <hi>Heliodorus</hi> has divided his work into ten Books.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not put among the number of Romances the Books of <hi>Paradoxes</hi> of <hi>Damaſcius,</hi> the Heathen Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, who lived under <hi>Juſtinian;</hi> for notwithſtonding <hi>Photius</hi> ſaith, that he imitated <hi>Antonius Diogenes,</hi> the model of moſt <hi>Greek</hi> Romancers, 'tis to be underſtood that he writ like him Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories Fabulous and Incredible, but not Romantick, nor after the manner of Romances; he relating onely the apparitions of Spectres, and Goblins, and Events above Nature, either too lightly believed, or invented with little addreſs, and becoming the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm and impiety of the Author.</p>
            <p>Two years after <hi>Damaſcius</hi> was the Hiſtory of <hi>Barlaam</hi> and <hi>Joſephat</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by St. <hi>John Damaſcenus.</hi> Many ancient Manuſcripts father it on <hi>John</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:107064:36"/>the <hi>Sinaite,</hi> who lived in the time of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> but without reaſon as <hi>Billius</hi> makes it appear; becauſe the diſputes againſt the <hi>Iconoclaſts,</hi> which are inſerted in this work, were not then moved, nor were till long time after by the Emperour <hi>Leon Iſanricus;</hi> under whom lived St. <hi>John Damaſcenus.</hi> 'Tis a Romance, but a Spiritual one; it treats of Love, but 'tis the love of God; and there one may find much blood ſpilt, but 'tis the blood of Martyrs: it is writ in the faſhion of a Hiſtory, not according to the rules of Romance, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that the veriſimility is there exactly enough obſerved. It bears with it ſo many marks of Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that it is not to be read but with ſome little diſcernment to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it. In the reſt one may perceive the fabulous <hi>Genius</hi> of the Authors Nation, by the great number of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boles, Compariſons and Similutudes,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:107064:37"/>which are there in abundance.</p>
            <p>The Romance of <hi>Theodorus Prodro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> and that which ſome attribute to <hi>Euſtathius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> who flouriſhed under the Empire of of <hi>Manuel Comines,</hi> about the middle of the twelfth Age, are much what of the ſame nature: the firſt contains the Amours of <hi>Doſicles</hi> and <hi>Rhodanthe,</hi> the other, thoſe of <hi>Aſmenas</hi> and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mene.</hi> Monſieur <hi>Gaulmen</hi> has made both of them publick together with his tranſlation and notes. Seeing he ſaith nothing of <hi>Euſtathius</hi> in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Book which bears his Name, I will interpret his ſilence in his favour; and believe that being a Learned Man, he fell not into the error of thoſe who are perſwaded that the famous Comentator upon <hi>Homer</hi> was capable of making ſuch a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable work as that is. Moreoverſome Manuſcripts name the Author <hi>Euma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius,</hi> and not <hi>Euſtathius;</hi> however
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:107064:37"/>the matter be, nothing is more frigid, nothing more flat, nothing more tedeous, no decorum, no veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimility, no conduct; 'tis the work of ſome School Boy, or ſome wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Pedagogue, who deſerved to be a School Boy all the days of his life. <hi>Theodorus Prodromus</hi> is not much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, however he has ſomething more of art though it be but little, he never extricates himſelf unleſs it be by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines, and he underſtands not how to make the Actors preſerve decorum, and the uniformity of their Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters. His work is rather a Poem then a Romance, for it is writ in Verſe, and this makes his ſtyle (which is too licentious and full of Figures) more pardonable; nevertheleſs ſeeing his Verſes are <hi>Iambicks,</hi> which are like Proſe and which may be called meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Proſe, I exclude him not from this laſt. Some ſay he was a <hi>Ruſſian</hi> by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a Prieſt, a Poet, a Philoſopher, and a Phyſitian.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:107064:38"/>
            <p>I give well nigh the ſame judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Longus</hi> the Sophiſt his Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, as of the two former Romances; for notwithſtanding that moſt of the Learned of late times have commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them for their elegance, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment joyned with a ſimplicity proper for the Subject; nevertheleſs I find nothing in all this but a ſimplicity, which runs ſometimes even to chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhneſs and foolery. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it, either of invention or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. He begins groſly with the Birth of his Shepheards, and ends with their Marriage; he never cleares up his Adventures but by Machines, improper and ill contrived; ſo obſcene for the reſt, that one muſt be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what a Cynick to read him without bluſhing. His ſtyle, which has been ſo much cryed up, is ſuch as may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves leſſe: 'tis the ſtyle of a Sophiſt, ſuch as he was, like that of <hi>Euſtathius</hi> and <hi>Theodorus Prodromus;</hi> which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:107064:38"/>of the <hi>Orator</hi> and the Hiſtorian, and which is proper neither to the one nor to the other; full of Metaphors, Antitheſes, and ſparkling Figures, which dazle and ſurprize the ſimple, and tickle the Ear, without ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the mind; in leju of ingaging the Reader by the novelty of the events, by the arangement and varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of matter, and by a clear and cloſe Narration, which withall has its cadence, goes off roundly, and which always advanceth within the ſubject. He aſſays (as moſt of other Sophiſts) to entertain him with deſcriptions by the by; he leads him out of the way, and while he lets him ſee ſo much of the Countrey which he did not look for, he ſpends and conſumes his attention, and the impatience he had to arrive at the end he ſought for and propoſed to himſelf. I tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated this Romance with delight in my Childhood, and it is that age on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:107064:39"/>which it can pleaſe: I ſhall not tell you in what time he lived; none of the Ancients have made mention of him, and he bears no token which may give place for conjectures, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs perhaps it be the purity of his ſtyle, which makes me judge him more ancient then the two former.</p>
            <p>For the three <hi>Xenophons</hi> Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, whereof <hi>Suidas</hi> ſpeaks, I can ſay no more of them then he has done: one of them was of <hi>Antioch,</hi> an other of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the third of <hi>Cyprus.</hi> All three writ Love ſtories: the firſt gave his Book the name of <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks,</hi> as <hi>Iamblicus:</hi> the ſecond Intitled his the <hi>Epheſia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks,</hi> and relates the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of <hi>Habr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>comas</hi> and <hi>Anthea:</hi> and the third named his the <hi>Cypriacks,</hi> where he recounts the Amours of <hi>Cinyras, Myrrha,</hi> and <hi>Adonis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ought not to forget <hi>Parthenius</hi> of <hi>Nicaea,</hi> from whom we have a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of love Hiſtories, which he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:107064:39"/>Dedicates to the Poet <hi>Cornelius Gallus</hi> of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his time. Many of them are drawn from the ancient Fable, and all from ancient Authors which he cites. Some of them ſeem Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and to have been taken from <hi>Mileſian</hi> Fables; as that of <hi>Erippe</hi> and <hi>Zanthus</hi> in the 8th. Chapter, that of <hi>Policrites</hi> and <hi>Deognete</hi> in the 9th. Chapter, that of <hi>Lucone</hi> and <hi>Cyonippe</hi> in the 10th. Chapter, and that of <hi>Neaere</hi> and <hi>Hypſicreon,</hi> and of <hi>Promedon</hi> in the 18th. Chapter, for beſides that theſe Adventures are attributed to <hi>Mileſian</hi> perſons, it doth not at all appear that they have been taken ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Fable or ancient Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The ſame may be ſaid of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of <hi>Cannus</hi> and <hi>Biblis,</hi> children of the Founder of <hi>Miletus,</hi> which he reports in the 11th. Chapter, are a Fiction of the Countries, which has made it famous, and has been conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated in the Antique Mythology.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:107064:40"/>This however I offer only as a ſlight conjecture.</p>
            <p>In this account which I make, I diſtinguiſh the regular Romances from thoſe which are not. I call re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular thoſe which are according to the rules of an Heroick Poem. The <hi>Greeks</hi> who have ſo happily improved moſt of Arts and Sciences, that one may account them the Inventors, have alſo cultivated the art of making Romances, and from rude and wild as it was among the <hi>Orientals,</hi> they have given it a better ſhape, adjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to the rules of the <hi>Epopee,</hi> and joyning in one complete body the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe parts, which without order or harmony compoſed the Romances of former times. Of all the <hi>Greek</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancers which I have named, they who have obſerved theſe rules are onely <hi>Antonius, Diogenes, Lucian, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenagoras, Iamblicus, Heliodorus, Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Tatius, Enſtathius,</hi> and <hi>Theodorus
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:107064:40"/>Prodromus.</hi> I do not mention <hi>Lucius</hi> of <hi>Patras,</hi> nor <hi>Damaſcius,</hi> whom I have not rancked among the makers of Romances; for St. <hi>John Damaſcenus</hi> and <hi>Longus,</hi> it had been eaſie for them to have reduced their works under theſe Laws, but they either were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of them, or deſpiſed them. I know not what to ſay of the three <hi>Xenophons,</hi> of whom nothing is left us: neither of <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> and thoſe who like him writ the <hi>Mileſian Fables.</hi> I believe however that theſe later were tyed to ſome rules and meaſures, which I judge by the works made in their imitation, which time has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved us, as the Metamorphoſis of <hi>Apuleus,</hi> which is regular enough.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Mileſian</hi> Fables, long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they made this Progreſs in <hi>Greece</hi> which you have ſeen, were already paſſed into <hi>Italy,</hi> and were there firſt received by the <hi>Sybarites,</hi> a people more Voluptuous then one can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:107064:41"/>This conformity of humour which they had with the <hi>Mileſians,</hi> eſtabliſhed among them a reciprocal commerce of luxury and pleaſure; and united them ſo well, that <hi>Hero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> aſſures us, he knew no people ſo ſtrictly allied; they then learned of the <hi>Mileſians</hi> the art of Fictions; and <hi>Sybaritick</hi> Fables were as common in <hi>Italy,</hi> as the <hi>Mileſian</hi> Fables were in <hi>Aſia;</hi> it is not eaſie to ſay what was their model, <hi>Heſychius</hi> gives us to underſtand in one paſſage very much corrupted, that <hi>Aeſop</hi> being in <hi>Italy,</hi> his Fables there were ſo well appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that they did improve upon them, and named them <hi>Sybariticks</hi> when they were changed, and they became a Proverb: but he diſcovers not wherein conſiſted that alteration. <hi>Suidas</hi> believed that they were like thoſe of <hi>Aeſop;</hi> he is miſtaken in this as frequently elſe where. The old Comentator upon <hi>Ariſtophones</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:107064:41"/>that the <hi>Sabarites</hi> made uſe of Beaſts in their Fables, and <hi>Aeſop</hi> made uſe of men in his; this paſſage is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly corrupted, for as it appears that <hi>Aeſops</hi> Fables imployed Beaſts, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that thoſe of the <hi>Sybarites</hi> made uſe of Men: and thus too he ſaith in an other place in expreſs terms; thoſe of the <hi>Sybarites</hi> were pleaſant and provoked laughter. I find a piece of one of them in <hi>Elian:</hi> 'tis a little ſtory which he ſaith he took from the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the <hi>Sybarites,</hi> that is to ſay, as I take it, from the <hi>Sybaritick</hi> Fables, you may judge there of by the ſtory it ſelf.</p>
            <p>A Child of <hi>Sybaris</hi> going to School along with his School-Maſter met in the Street one that ſold Figgs, and ſtole from him one of them; the Schoolmaſter ſharply reproving him, ſnatches the Fig from him, &amp; eats it.</p>
            <p>But theſe Fables were not onely facetious but ſmutty withall. <hi>Ovid</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:107064:42"/>puts the <hi>Sybaritida,</hi> which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſome little time before him, among the number of the moſt laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious pieces. Many Learned Men believe that he intends the work of <hi>Hemitheon</hi> the <hi>Sybarite,</hi> whereof <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> ſpeaks, as of a maſs of ſmuttineſs: this appears to me without ground, for one cannot at all perceive that the <hi>Sybaritida</hi> did any other wiſe agree with the Book of <hi>Hemitheon,</hi> then in this, that both the one and the other were Books of Debauchery; and this was common to all the <hi>Sybaritick</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. Bbeſides this the <hi>Sybaritida</hi> was made but a little before <hi>Ovids</hi> time; whereas the Town of <hi>Sybares</hi> was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely ruined, by the <hi>Crotoniates</hi> 500 years before him. 'Tis therefore more credible that this <hi>Sybaritida</hi> was compoſed by ſome <hi>Roman</hi> and ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, becauſe it was made in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ancient <hi>Sybaritick</hi> Fables. A certain old Author, whoſe name I
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:107064:42"/>believe you do not much value, gives us to underſtand that their ſtyle was curt and <hi>Laconick;</hi> but all this doth not convince us that theſe Fables had nothing of the Romance in them.</p>
            <p>This paſſage of <hi>Ovid</hi> makes it clear, that in his time the <hi>Romans</hi> had given admittance to the Fables of the <hi>Sybarites</hi> amongſt them: and he teaches us in the ſame Book, that the famous Hiſtorian <hi>Siſenna</hi> had alſo tranſlated for them the <hi>Mileſian</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of <hi>Ariſtides.</hi> This <hi>Siſenna</hi> lived in <hi>Sylla's</hi> time, and was with him of the great and Illuſtrious Family of the <hi>Cornelians:</hi> He was Praetor of <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Acaia;</hi> he writ the Hiſtory of his Countrey, and was preſerred before all Hiſtorians of his Nation, who went before him.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Roman</hi> Republick diſdeigned not the reading of theſe Fables then, while it yet retained an auſtere Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and rigid manners; 'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:107064:43"/>if being fallen under the power of the Emperours, and after their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being abandoned to luxury and pleaſures, it was likewiſe toucht with thoſe which Romances gave the mind. <hi>Virgil,</hi> who lived a little after the firſt riſe of the Empire, gives not any more agreeable diverſion to the <hi>Naides,</hi> Daughters of the River <hi>Peneus,</hi> while they were aſſembled together under their Fathers Waters, then to relate the Amours of the Gods, which were the ſubject of the Romances of Antiquity.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Ovid, Virgils</hi> contemporary, makes the Daughters of <hi>Menius</hi> tell Romantick Tales; and while their hands were buſie and employed, their tongues and wit were at liberty. The firſt is of the Loves of <hi>Pyramus</hi> and <hi>Thisbe;</hi> the ſecond of thoſe of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus;</hi> the third of thoſe of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macis</hi> for <hi>Hermaphrodite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this appears the eſteem <hi>Rome</hi> heretofore had for Romances, which
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:107064:43"/>is yet more clear by the Romance which <hi>Petronius</hi> (one of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, and the moſt poliſhed man of his time) compoſed; he made it in form of a <hi>Satyr,</hi> of that kind which <hi>Varre</hi> had invented, intermixing agreeably Proſe with Verſe, and the ſerious with the jocoſe, the which he named <hi>Menippian;</hi> becauſe <hi>Menippus</hi> before him had treated of grave matters, in a pleaſant and ſcoffing ſtyle.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Satyr</hi> of <hi>Petronius</hi> fails not to be a true Romance; it contains no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but agreeable and ingenious Fictions, but very often too wanton and immodeſt. Hiding under the bark a fine and tart raillery againſt the vices of <hi>Nero's</hi> Court. Seeing what remains of it are onely ſome fragments, which ſcarce have any coherence at all one with another, or rather the collections of ſome indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious perſon; one cannot exactly diſcern the form and tiſſue of the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:107064:44"/>whole piece, nevertheleſs it appears to be conducted with order. And 'tis probable the incoherent parts would make up a complete body with thoſe that are wanting. Though <hi>Petronius</hi> ſeems to be a very great Critick, and of an exquiſite taſte in learning, his ſtyle does not always altogether an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the delicatneſs of his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſomething of affectation may be obſerved; he is ſomewhat too much Painted and Studied, and degenerates from that natural and majeſtick ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of the happy age of <hi>Auguſtus.</hi> So true is it that the art of ſpeaking, which all the World practiſes (and which ſo very few underſtand) is yet much eaſier to underſtand then to practiſe well.</p>
            <p>Some ſay that the Poet <hi>Lucan,</hi> who alſo lived in <hi>Nero's</hi> time, compoſed <hi>Saltick</hi> Fables, that is (as ſome think) fables wherein are recounted the loves of <hi>Satyrs</hi> and <hi>Nymphs.</hi> This agrees well
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:107064:44"/>with a Romance, and the wit of that Age, which was Romantick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms my ſuſpicion. But in regard nothing is left us but the Title, and that too does not clearly enough ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the nature of the piece, I ſhall ſay nothing thereof.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> of <hi>Apuleus,</hi> ſo well known under the Title of the <hi>Golden Aſs,</hi> was made under the <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nins.</hi> It had the ſame Original with the <hi>Aſs</hi> of <hi>Lucian,</hi> being taken out of the two firſt Books of the Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſes of <hi>Lucius</hi> of <hi>Patras,</hi> with this difference always, that theſe Books were abridged by <hi>Lucian,</hi> and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by <hi>Apuleus.</hi> The work of this Philoſopher is regular, for not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he ſeems to begin with his infancy, yet what is there ſaid is onely by way of Preface, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the Barbarouſneſs of his ſtyle. The true beginning of his Hiſtory is at his Voyage into <hi>Theſſalia.</hi> He has
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:107064:45"/>given us an <hi>Idea</hi> of the <hi>Mileſian</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in this piece, which he declares withall to be of that ſort; he has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched it with pretty <hi>Epiſodes,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others with that of <hi>Pſyche,</hi> which no perſon is ignorant of; and he has not at all retrencht the ſmutti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which was in the Originals which he had followed. His ſtyle is that of a Sophiſt, full of affectation and violent figures, hard, barbarous, and befitting an <hi>African.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some hold that <hi>Clodius Albinus,</hi> one of the pretenders to the Empire, who was vanquiſht and ſlain by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Severus,</hi> diſdained not a like travail. <hi>Julius Capitolinus</hi> reports in his life, that there were ſeen certain <hi>Mileſian</hi> Fables under his name, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed, though but indifferently written; and that <hi>Severus</hi> reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Senate, that they had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him for a Learned Man, whereas he read nothing but the <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:107064:45"/>Fables of <hi>Apuleus,</hi> and ſpent all his Study in old Wives tales and ſuch like trifles, which he preferred before ſerious employments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martianus Capella</hi> has (as <hi>Petronius</hi>) given the name of <hi>Satyr</hi> to his work, for that it is writ like his in Verſe and Proſe; and that the profitable and the agreeable are there interwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; having deſign to treat of all thoſe which are called the Liberal Arts, he therefore takes a circumference, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them perſons; and feigning that <hi>Mercury,</hi> who has them in his Train, Eſpouſes <hi>Philology,</hi> that is to ſay, the love of good Letters, and gives her for a Nuptial preſent whatever they have moſt fair and moſt precious; ſo that it is a continual Allegory, which properly deſerves not the name of a Romance, but rather of a Fable: for as I have already remarqued, a Fable repreſents things which never have nor ever can happen; and a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:107064:46"/>Romance repreſents things which may, but never have happened. The artifice of this Allegory is not very ſubtile; the ſtyle is barbariſme it ſelf; ſo bold and ſo extravagant in his fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, that they were not to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned the moſt deſperate Poet; and covered with an obſcurity ſo thick, that it is hardly intelligible: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is Learned and full of Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are not common.</p>
            <p>Some write that the Author was an <hi>African,</hi> if he were not he might well be one, his manner of writing is ſo harſh and forced. The time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he lived is not known, it onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears he was more ancient then <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto the Art of Romancing was maintained with ſome ſplendour, but it declined afterwards with Learning and the Empire, when theſe boyſterous Nations of the <hi>North</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried every where with them their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:107064:46"/>and barbarity. Before Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances were made for delight; now were deviſed fabulous Hiſtories, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none were acquainted with the Truth. <hi>Talieſſin,</hi> who is ſaid to have lived about the middle of the ſixth Age, under that King <hi>Arthur</hi> ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in Romances; and <hi>Melkin</hi> who was ſomewhat younger, writ the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>England,</hi> their Countrey, of King <hi>Arthur,</hi> and of the round Table. <hi>Balaus,</hi> who has put them in his Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, ſpeaks of them as of Authors filled with Fables. The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Hunibaldus Francus,</hi> who was (as ſome write) contemporary of <hi>Clovis,</hi> and whoſe Hiſtory is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but a maſs of lyes groſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p>In fine, Sir, we come to the famous Book of the exploits of <hi>Charlemagne,</hi> which ſome aſcribe very untowardly to the Archbiſhop <hi>Turpin,</hi> though he be later then it by more then two
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:107064:47"/>hundred years. <hi>Pigna</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have believed ridiculouſly, that Romances took their name from the Town of <hi>Reims,</hi> whereof he was Archbiſhop, for that his Book (as <hi>Pigna</hi> reports) was the Source from whence the Romances of <hi>Provence</hi> chiefly iſſued; and that he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to others the principal among the makers of Romances.</p>
            <p>However there are to be ſeen many Hiſtories of <hi>Charlemagnes</hi> life full of extravagant Fables, and like that which bears the name of <hi>Turpin.</hi> Such were the Hiſtories attributed to <hi>Harcon,</hi> and to <hi>Solcon Forteman;</hi> to <hi>Savard the Sage,</hi> to <hi>Adell Adeling,</hi> and to <hi>John</hi> Son of the King of <hi>Freez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> all five <hi>Freezlanders;</hi> and who are alſo ſaid to have lived in the time of <hi>Charlemagne.</hi> Such alſo was the Hiſtory attributed to <hi>Occon,</hi> who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the common opinion was Contemporary of <hi>Otho the Great,</hi> and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:107064:47"/>had <hi>Solcon</hi> before named to his great Uncle. And ſuch were thoſe which contain the Atchievments of King <hi>Arthur,</hi> and the Life of <hi>Merlin.</hi> Theſe Hiſtories compoſed for delight plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Readers, who were ſimple and more ignorant then thoſe who made them; they did not in thoſe days trouble themſelves in the reſearches after good Memoires, and in being informed of the truth for writing of Hiſtories. They had the ſtuff in their own head, and went no farther then their own invention. Thus Hiſtorians degenerated into true Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancers. In this Age of ignorance the Latine Tongue too as well as truth was deſpiſed. The Verſifiers, Compoſers, Inventers of Tales, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and in fine thoſe of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey who ſtudied that which was there called the <hi>Gay Science,</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin about the time of <hi>Hugh Capet</hi> to Romance it <hi>pell mell;</hi> and over run
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:107064:48"/>
               <hi>France,</hi> giving about their Romances, and Fables compoſed in the <hi>Roman</hi> Tongue; for heretofore thoſe of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence</hi> had more of Learning and Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie among them, then all <hi>France</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. This <hi>Roman</hi> Tongue was that which the <hi>Romans</hi> introducted among the <hi>Gauls</hi> together with their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts; and which being corrupted by the times with a mixture of the <hi>Gauliſh</hi> Language which was before, and then <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Tudeſque</hi> which followed, 'twas neither <hi>Latin, Gauliſh,</hi> nor <hi>French,</hi> but a certain medley of all, wherein <hi>Latin</hi> however was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant, the which for that reaſon was always called the <hi>Roman,</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh it from the particular and natural Language of each Countrey, as the <hi>French, Gauliſh</hi> or <hi>Celtique, Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanique, Belgique;</hi> for <hi>Caſer</hi> writs that theſe three Languages were different among themſelves, which <hi>Strabo</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of a difference, which only was
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:107064:48"/>as the diverſe dialects of the ſame Language.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniard</hi> uſe the word <hi>Romancé</hi> in the ſame ſignification with us, and they call their ordinary language <hi>Romancé</hi>; the <hi>Romain</hi> being then moſt univerſally undeſtood, thoſe of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence</hi> who Studied Fictons made uſe thereof for their Fictions, which from thence were called Romances. The Verſifiers alſo travaling about the Countrey, were bountifully rewarded for their labours, and nobly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Lords, whom they made vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits to; ſome whereof would be ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported with delight to hear them, that they ſometimes would even de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoil themſelves of their Robes to adorn the Verſifiers therewithall. Thoſe of <hi>Provence</hi> were not the onely perſons who delighted in this agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able exerciſe: almoſt every Province of <hi>France</hi> had their Romancers, even to <hi>Picardy,</hi> where were compoſed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:107064:49"/>their <hi>Servantois,</hi> pieces treating of Love, and ſometimes Satyrical: and from thence come ſo very many of old Romances, whereof ſome part are Printed, others are rotting in Libraries, the reſt conſumed by the length of time. <hi>Spain</hi> it ſelf, which has been ſo fruitful in Romances, and <hi>Italy</hi> too, have from us received the art of compoſing them. <hi>Mi par di poter dire che queſta ſorte di Poeſia:</hi> Theſe are the words of <hi>Giraldi</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Romances. <hi>Habbia haunta la prima Origine, &amp; il primo ſuo principio da</hi> Franceſi, <hi>da' i quali ha forſe onco haveto il nome. Da</hi> Francéſi <hi>pio e paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta queſta maniera di peteggiare a gli</hi> Spagnuoli, <hi>&amp; ultimamonte e ſtata ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cettata da gli</hi> Italiani. <q>So that I may ſay this ſort of Poeſie has had its firſt Original and Source from the <hi>French,</hi> and from them peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture took the name. From the <hi>French</hi> afterwards this kind of Poetizing
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:107064:49"/>paſſed to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and laſtly was entertained by the <hi>Italians.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The late <hi>Salmaſius,</hi> whoſe memorie I have in ſingular veneration, both for his great Learning, and for the friendſhip which was contracted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, was of opinion that <hi>Spain</hi> having learned of the <hi>Arabians</hi> the art of making Romances, did afterwards communicate it by their example to all the reſt of <hi>Europe.</hi> To maintain this one muſt hold that <hi>Talieſſin</hi> and <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin</hi> both <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Hunnibaldus Francus,</hi> (which three are believed to have compoſed their Romantick Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories about the year 550) are more recent by at leaſt about 200 years then can be imagined. For the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of <hi>Comte Julian,</hi> and entrance of the <hi>Arab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ans</hi> into <hi>Spain,</hi> happened not till 91 of the <hi>Hegira,</hi> that is to ſay, the 712 year of our Lord; and ſome time muſt be allowed for theſe Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of the <hi>Arabians</hi> to ſpread in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:107064:50"/>
               <hi>Spain,</hi> and for thoſe which (as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) the <hi>Spaniards</hi> made in their imitation to be diſperſed throughout the reſt of <hi>Europe.</hi> I ſhall not take upon me to maintain the antiquity of theſe Authors, though I have ſome right ſo to do, ſeeing the common and received opinion is for me. 'Tis certain that the <hi>Arabians</hi> were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly addicted (as I have made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear) to the <hi>Gay Science,</hi> I mean to Poeſie, Fables, and Fictions. This Science having continued with them while it was rude, without having been improved and cultivated by the <hi>Greeks.</hi> They brought it along with their Arms into <hi>Africa</hi> when they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued it; though beſides it had always flouriſhed among the <hi>Africans;</hi> for <hi>Areſtole</hi> and after him <hi>Priſcian</hi> make mention of the <hi>Lybick</hi> Fables, and the Romances of <hi>Apateus</hi> and <hi>Martianus Capella Aſricans,</hi> whereof I before have ſpoken, ſhew that it was the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:107064:50"/>wit of theſe people; and this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced much to the fortifying of the victorious <hi>Arabians</hi> in their inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. We likewiſe learn out of <hi>Leo, Afer</hi> and <hi>Marmol,</hi> that the <hi>Africain A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabians</hi> do ſtill paſſionately love Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick Poeſie, and that they ſing in Verſe and Proſe the exploits of their <hi>Buhaluh,</hi> as among us are celebrated thoſe of <hi>Arthur</hi> and <hi>Lancelot;</hi> that their <hi>Morabites</hi> compoſe Love Ditties, that in <hi>Fez</hi> on <hi>Mahumets</hi> Birth-day the Poets have their aſſemblies and publick ſports, and repeat their Verſes before the people; and who in their judgement had done beſt, is created Prince of the Poets for that year; that the Kings of the Houſe of the <hi>Benimerinis,</hi> who have Reigned this three hundred years, and which our old Writers call <hi>Bellemarine,</hi> aſſemble on a certain day every year the moſt able Judges in the City of <hi>Fez,</hi> and makes them a moſt ſpendid Feaſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:107064:51"/>which the Poets repeat their Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es in honour of <hi>Mahumet;</hi> that the King beſtows on him who excels the reſt a ſum of Money, a Horſe, a Slave, and his own Robes, which he wore that day; and that none of the reſt return home without recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spain</hi> having received the yoak of the <hi>Arabians</hi> learned withall their manners, and took from them the cuſtom of ſinging love Verſes, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrating the actions of great Men after the faſhion of the Bards among the <hi>Gauls;</hi> but theſe Songs which they named <hi>Romances,</hi> were much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from what is called a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, for they were poeſies made to be Sung, and conſequently very ſhort. Some have made a collection of many of them, ſome whereof are ſo Ancient, that they can hardly be underſtood; and they have ſometimes ſerved to clear up, and explain the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:107064:51"/>Hiſtories of <hi>Spain,</hi> and to reduce the events to order in Chronology. Their <hi>Romances</hi> are much later, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienteſt of them are of nothing ſo old a date as our Sir <hi>Triſtrams</hi> and <hi>Lance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots.</hi> For ſome Centuries of years <hi>Miguel de Cervante,</hi> one of the beſt wits <hi>Spain</hi> has produced, made a fine and judicious Critique in his <hi>Don Quixot;</hi> and hardly could the <hi>Curate</hi> of the <hi>Marcha,</hi> and Maiſtre <hi>Nicolas</hi> the <hi>Barber,</hi> find in ſo vaſt a number ſix which were worthy to be preſerved; the reſt are <hi>delivered over to the ſecular arm of the old Wife,</hi> to be put in the fire. Thoſe which they judged worth the keeping, were the four Books of <hi>Amadis de Gaul,</hi> which is ſaid to be the firſt Romance of Chivalry, which was Printed in <hi>Spain,</hi> the model and beſt of all the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Palmerin</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> which ſome believe was compoſed by a King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and which they judge worthy
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:107064:52"/>to be put in a Box, like that of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> wherein <hi>Alexander</hi> kept the Works of <hi>Homer. Don Beloanis,</hi> the Mirrour of Chivalry: <hi>Tirante the White,</hi> and <hi>Kyrie Eleiſon</hi> of <hi>Montauban,</hi> (for in the good old times it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that <hi>Kyrie Eleiſon</hi> and <hi>Poralipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menon</hi> were the names of ſome Saints) where the ſubtleties of Madam <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure-of-my-Life,</hi> with the Love and Guyles of Widow <hi>Repoſada</hi> are highly extolled. But all this is but of yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in compariſon of our old Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, which in all probability were the Models and Originals of them, as the conformity of the works and vicirity of the Nations may perſwade. He alſo gives his cenſure upon the Romances in Verſe, and other Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies which were found in the Library of <hi>Don Quixot;</hi> but this is beſide our Subject.</p>
            <p>If any object that as we took from the <hi>Arabians</hi> the art of Ryming, 'tis
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:107064:52"/>credible that we had from them alſo the Art of Romancing: ſeeing that the moſt part of our old Romances were in rvme, and that the cuſtom of the <hi>French</hi> Lords, to give their Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the beſt Poets, and which <hi>Marm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> ſaith was practiſed by the Kings of <hi>Fez,</hi> gives yet more ground for this ſuſpicion. I allow that it is not altogether impoſſible that the <hi>French</hi> learned time of the <hi>Arabians,</hi> having taken from them likewiſe the uſage of applying it to Romances. I allow alſo that the love we then had for Fables, might be augmented and fortified by their example, and that our art Romantick was (it may be) enriched by the Commerce which the Neighbourhood of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the Wars gave us with them: but not at all that we are endebted to them for this inclination, ſeeing that it poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed us long time before it was taken notice of in <hi>Spain;</hi> neither can I more
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:107064:53"/>believe that the Princes of <hi>France</hi> took from the <hi>Arabian</hi> Kings that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of deſpoiling themſelves of their Garments in ſavour of the <hi>Poets.</hi> I rather think, that both the one and thed other touched with the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the works they heard repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they could not hold from exerting their liberality immediately; and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing more near or ready then their habits, they made uſe of them for that occaſion: as we read of ſome Saints, who have done the like for the poor; and that this which often came to paſs in <hi>France</hi> by accident, is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed every year at <hi>Fez</hi> by cuſtom, probably was there too at firſt intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by chance only.</p>
            <p>It is very credible that the <hi>Italians</hi> were firſt brought to the compoſing of Romances, by the example of thoſe in <hi>Provence,</hi> then when the Popes held their Sea at <hi>Avignon;</hi> and even by the example of other <hi>French,</hi> then
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:107064:53"/>when the <hi>Normans</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> Comte d' <hi>Anjou</hi> (Brother to Saint <hi>Louis</hi>) a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Prince, a lover of Poeſie, and a Poet himſelf, made War in <hi>Italy;</hi> for the <hi>Normans</hi> alſo would be tampering with the <hi>Gray Science.</hi> And Hiſtory reports, that they ſung the deeds of <hi>Roland</hi> before they gave that memor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Battail, which won the Crown of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Baſtard.</hi> All <hi>Europe</hi> in thoſe days was covered with darkneſs and thick ignorance; but <hi>France, England,</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> leſs then <hi>Italy,</hi> which then produced but a ſmall number of Writers, and ſcarce any makers of Romances at all. Thoſe of that Countrey, who had a mind to make themſelves diſtinguiſhed by ſome tincture of knowledge, came for it to the Univerſity of <hi>Paris;</hi> which was the mother of Sciences, and Nource of the Learned of <hi>Europe.</hi> St. <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> St. <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> the Poet <hi>Danfe,</hi> and <hi>Bocace</hi> came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:107064:54"/>to Study, and the Preſident <hi>Fauchet</hi> ſhews that this laſt took moſt part of his Novels from <hi>French</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances; and that <hi>Petrarch</hi> and the other <hi>Italian</hi> Poets have pilfred the richeſt phanſies and conceits from the Songs of <hi>Thiband</hi> King of <hi>Navar,</hi> from <hi>Gaces Bruſſez,</hi> Chaſtelain <hi>de Corcy,</hi> and the old <hi>French</hi> Romancers. 'Twas then in my opinion, in this mixture of the two Nations, that the <hi>Italians</hi> learned from us the Science of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, which by their own confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion they owe to us as well as the Science of rimes.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> had from us an art, which was the fruit of our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and rudneſs, and which the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litneſs of the <hi>Perſians, Ionians,</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi> had produced. In effect as in neceſſity to preſerve our lives want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Bread, we nouriſh our Bodies with herbs and roots; ſo when the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of truth, which is the propre
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:107064:54"/>and natural Food of the mind begins to fail us, we nouriſh it with Lies, which are the imitation of truth; and as in plenty to ſatisfie our pleaſure, we often quit Bread and our ordinary Viands, for Ragouſts. Thus when our minds are acquainted with the truth, they often forſake the Study and ſpeculation thereof, to be divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Image of Truth, which is Fiction; for the Image and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to <hi>Ariſtole,</hi> are often more agreeable, then the truth it ſelf; ſo that two Paths directly oppoſite, which are ignorance and learning, rudeneſs and politneſs often carry Men to one and the ſame end, which is the Study of Fictions, Fables, and Romances. Hence it is that the moſt Barbarous Nations love Romantick inventions, as well as thoſe which are the moſt poliſht. The Origines of all the Savages of <hi>America,</hi> and particularly thoſe of <hi>Peru,</hi> contain
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:107064:55"/>nothing but Fables; no otherwiſe then the Origines of the <hi>Goths,</hi> which they writ heretofore in their ancient <hi>Runick</hi> Characters upon great ſtones; whereof I have ſeen ſome remains in <hi>Denmark.</hi> And if ought were left us of thoſe Works which the <hi>Bards</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Ancient <hi>Gauls</hi> compoſed to eterniſe the memory of their Nation, I queſtion not at all but we ſhould find them inricht with abundance of Fictions.</p>
            <p>This inclination to Fables, which is common to all Men, is not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of ratiocination, imitation or cuſtom. 'Tis natural to them, and has its bait in the very frame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of their mind and ſoul; for the deſire to know and to learn is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to man, and no leſs does di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh him from other creatures then his reaſon. One may find even in other creatures ſome ſparks of a rude and imperfect reaſon; but the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:107064:55"/>coveting of knowledge was never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, ſave in Man only.</p>
            <p>This proceeds (according to my ſenſe) from that, that the faculties of our Soul being of too vaſt an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and of a capacity too large to be filled by the preſent objects; the Soul does ranſack and ſearch in what is paſt, and what is to come, in truth and in fictions, in imaginary ſpaces and in impoſſibility, for wherewith to exerciſe and employ it. <hi>Brutes</hi> find in the objects which preſent themſelves to their ſenſe wherewith to ſatisfie the powers of their Soul, and are not concerned further; ſo that one ſees not in them this reſtleſs deſire which agitates inceſſantly the mind of Men, and carries it to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearch of new knowledge; to propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (if poſſible) the object to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, and find there a pleaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, that we enjoy in appeaſing a violent hunger, or quenching a long
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:107064:56"/>thirſt. 'Tis this <hi>Plato</hi> would expreſs by the Fable of the Marriage of <hi>Porus</hi> and <hi>Penia,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Riches</hi> and <hi>Poverty,</hi> whereof he ſaith, is born pleaſure, the object is ſignified by Riches, which are not riches but in the uſage, and otherwiſe remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful, and in no wiſe beget plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. The faculty is intended by Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, which is ſterile, and always attended with inquietude, while it is ſeperated from Riches; but when it is joyned thereunto, pleaſure is the iſſue of this union. All this we meet withall exactly in our ſoul; Poverty, that is to ſay, ignorance is natural to it, and it ſighs continually after Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which is its riches; which when it is poſſeſsed of, this enjoyment is followed by pleaſure; but this pleaſure is not always equal, it often coſteth it much pains and traval; as when the ſoul applyes it ſelf to diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult ſpeculations, and occult Sciences,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:107064:56"/>the matter whereof is not preſent to our ſenſes, and where the imagination which acts with facility has a leſs part then the underſtanding whoſe opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are more laborious; and for that labour is naturally irckſome to us; the ſoulis not carryed to hard and ſpinous learning; unleſs in proſpect of the fruits, or in hopes of a remote pleaſure, or elſe by neceſſity; but the knowledge which attracts the ſoul and delights it moſt, is that which is acquired without pain, and where the imagination (in a manner) alone does act, and on matters like thoſe, which fall ordinarily under our ſenſe; and eſpecially if this knowledge ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites our paſſions, which are the great movers in all the actions of our life. Such are theſe Romances; there is required no great contention or tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the mind to comprehend them. No long reaſonings to be made, nor the memory over-burth-end,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:107064:57"/>nothing is required but the phancy; imagine onely and 'tis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. They move not our paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſave onely to appeaſe them; they ſtir not our fear or compaſſion, but to make us ſee out of danger or miſery thoſe we feared or complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for; they touch not our tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but to let us ſee them happy we had a love and tenderneſs for. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, all of our paſſions find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves there agreeably provoked and calmed. 'Tis therefore that they who act more by paſſion then by reaſon, and travail more with their imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then their underſtanding, are moſt taken therewith; though theſe other are ſo too, but after another manner. Theſe are touched with the beauties of Art, and that which proceeds from the intellect; but the former ſuch as are children and the ſimple, are ſenſible onely of that which ſtrikes their imagination, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:107064:57"/>ſtirs their paſſions, &amp; they love fictions in themſelves, without looking further. Now Fictions being nothing but nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, true in appearance and falſe in effect; the minds of the ſimple, who diſcern only the bark, are pleaſed with this ſhow of truth, and very well ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. But theſe who penetrate further, and ſee into the ſolid, are eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted with this falſity, ſo that the firſt love the falſehood, becauſe it is concealed under an appearance of truth; theſe others are diſtaſted with this Image of truth, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the real falſehood, which is couched under it; if this falſehood be not otherwiſe ingenious, myſterious, and inſtructive, and buoys it ſelf up by the excellence of the invention and art. And S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith ſomewhere, that theſe falſities which are ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and couch a hidden meaning, are not lyes, but the Figures of truth, which the moſt Sage and Holy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:107064:58"/>and our Saviour himſelf have made uſe on upon occaſion.</p>
            <p>Since then 'tis true that lyes ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily flow from ignorance, and the groſsneſs of our intellectuals, and that this inundation of the Barbarians, who iſsued from the <hi>North,</hi> ſpread o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all <hi>Europe,</hi> and plunged it in ſo profound an ignorance, as it could not clear it ſelf from, till after two Ages or thereabouts, is it not then very probable that this ignorance cauſed the ſame effect in <hi>Europe,</hi> which it always had produced every where beſides; and is it not in vain to ſeek for that in chance, which we find in nature? there is then no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to contend, but that <hi>French, Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Romances, and all the Fables of the <hi>North</hi> are of the Countrey's growth, born upon the place, and not imported from elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; that they never had other Original then the Hiſtories ſtuff with
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:107064:58"/>falſities, and made in obſcure and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant times, when there was neither induſtry nor curioſity to diſcover the truth of things, nor art for diſcribing it: that theſe Hiſtories mixed with true and falſe, having been well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the rude and half-barbarous people; the Hiſtorians thereupon took the boldneſs to preſent them ſuch as were purely forged, which are the Romances. 'Tis alſo a common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that the name of Romance has been heretofore given to Hiſtories, and was applyed afterwards to Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which is an irrefragable teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that the one has come from the others <hi>Ramanzi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pigna, ſecondo la commune opinione in</hi> Franceſe <hi>detti erano gliannali, &amp; percio le Guerre di parte in parte notate ſotto queſto nome uſcivano, poſcia alcuni dalla verita partendoſi, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunque favoleggiaſſero, coſi apunto chia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morono li ſcritti loro.</hi> 
               <q>Romances ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the common opinion in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:107064:59"/>
                  <hi>France</hi> were the Annals; and for that the Hiſtory of the War publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed part after part had that Name, ſome afterwards who neglected the truth, howſoever Fabulous they were, gave their writings alſo the ſame Title.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Strabo</hi> in a paſſage I have already alledged, ſaith that the Hiſtories of the <hi>Perſians, Medes,</hi> and <hi>Syrians</hi> have not deſerved much credit; for that thoſe who writ them, ſeeing that the Inventers of Fables were in great eſteem, believed they might be ſo too, by writing of Fables in the form of Hiſtories, that is to ſay, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances: whence one may conclude that Romances, according to all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances and likelyhood have among us had the ſame Original, which they had heretofore among theſe people.</p>
            <p>But to return to the <hi>Troubadours</hi> or <hi>Trouverres</hi> [ſo were called theſe Poets] of <hi>Provence,</hi> who were the Princes of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:107064:59"/>Romancery in <hi>France,</hi> about the end of the tenth Age, their myſtery was ſo generally approved of, that all the Provinces of <hi>France,</hi> as I have ſaid, had alſo their <hi>Trouverres.</hi> They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in the eleventh Age a matchleſs multitude of Romances, both in Proſe and Verſe, many whereof maugre the envy of time, are preſerved even to our days. Of this number were the Romances of <hi>Garin le Loheran,</hi> of <hi>Triſtram,</hi> of <hi>Lancelot du Lake,</hi> of <hi>Bertain,</hi> of St. <hi>Greal,</hi> of <hi>Merlyn,</hi> of <hi>Arthur,</hi> of <hi>Perceval,</hi> of <hi>Perceforeſt,</hi> and of moſt part of thoſe 127 Poets, who lived before the year 1300. of whom the Preſident <hi>Fauchet</hi> has given his cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. I ſhall not undertake to make you a Catalogue of them, nor exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether the <hi>Amadis de Gaul</hi> be Originally from <hi>Spain, Flanders,</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> and whether the Romance of <hi>Tiel Uleſpiegel</hi> be a Tranſlation from the <hi>German,</hi> nor in what lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:107064:60"/>the Romance of the ſeven wiſe Men of <hi>Greece</hi> was firſt written, or that of <hi>Dolopathos;</hi> which ſome ſay was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the parables of <hi>Sandaban</hi> the <hi>Indian:</hi> ſome ſay likewiſe that it is to be found in <hi>Greek</hi> in ſome Libraries; which has furniſhed the matter of an <hi>Italian</hi> Book called <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> and of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Bocace</hi> his Novels, as the ſame <hi>Fauchet</hi> has remarked: which was writ in Latin by <hi>John, Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,</hi> of the Abbeyde <hi>Hauteſelue</hi> whereof anci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt Copies are to be ſeen; and Tranſlated into <hi>French</hi> by the Clerk <hi>Hebert,</hi> about the end of the twelfth Age, and into <hi>High Dutch</hi> about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>00 years after; and after an hundred years more, from <hi>High Dutch</hi> into Latin again by a Learned perſon, who changed the Names thereof, and was ignorant that the <hi>Dutch</hi> had come from the Latin. It will ſuffice that I tell you all theſe works, to which ignorance has given Birth, did bear along with them the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:107064:60"/>marks of their Original, and were no other then a fardle of Fictions groſly huddled together without head or foot, and infinitely ſhort of that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign degree of Art and Elegance, whereunto the <hi>French</hi> Nation has af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards brought Romances. 'Tis truely a ſubject of wonder, that hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yielded to others the Bayes for Epick Poeſie and Hiſtory, we have carried theſe to ſo high a pitch, that the beſt of their Romances do not equal the very meaneſt of ours.</p>
            <p>We owe I believe this advantage to the refinement and politneſs of our Galantry; which proceeds (in my opinion) from the great liberty in which the Men in <hi>France</hi> live with the Women: theſe are in a manner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſes in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from Men by ſo many obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, that they are ſcarce to be ſeen, and not to be ſpoken with at all. Wherefore Men have there neglected
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:107064:61"/>the art of cajoling them agreeably, becauſe the occaſions for it are ſo rare. All the ſtudy and buſineſs there is to ſurmount the difficulties of acceſs; and this being effected, they make uſe of the time without amuſing themſelves with forms. But in <hi>France</hi> the Dames go at large upon their Parole; and being under no cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody, but that of their own heart, make thereof a Fort more ſtrong and ſure then all the Keys and Grates, and all the vigilance of the <hi>Douegnaes.</hi> The Men hereby are obliged to lay a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall Siege to this Fort, and imploy ſo much induſtry and and addreſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it, that they have made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of an art, which ſcarce is known to other people. 'Tis this art which diſtinguiſhes the <hi>French</hi> from other Romances, and which renders the reading of them ſo delicious, that they have cauſed the more profitable read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be neglected. The Dames
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:107064:61"/>were the firſt taken with this bayt: Theſe made Romances their whole ſtudy, and have ſo deſpiced that of the ancient Fable and Hiſtory, that they now no longer underſtand thoſe works, from which they formerly received their chiefeſt accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that they may not bluſh at this ignorance, which they ſo often find themſelves guilty of, they perceive that they had better diſapprove what they are ignorant of, then take the pains to learn it. The men have imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated them, in complaiſance, and have condemned what they condemned, and called Pedantry that which made an eſſential part of politeſs, even in <hi>Malherbe</hi>'s time. The Poets and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>French</hi> Writers who ſucceeded, have been conſtrained to ſubmit to this judgement; and many among them ſeeing that the knowledge of antiquity was of no advantage to them, have ceaſed to ſtudy what they
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:107064:62"/>durſt no longer practiſe. Thus a good cauſe has produced a very ill effect, and the beauty of our Romances has drawn on the contempt of good Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and conſequently ignorance.</p>
            <p>Not that I pretend for all this to condemn the reading of them. The beſt things in the World are attended always with their inconveniences. Romances may have much worſe too then ignorance. I know what they are accuſed for: they drain our devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they inſpire as with irregular paſſions, and corrupt our manners. All this may be, and ſometimes does hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen. But what cannot evil and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward minds make a bad uſe on? weak ſouls are even contageous to themſelves and make poyſon of every thing: Hiſtories muſt be forbidden, which relates ſo many pernicious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples; and the Fable, for there crimes are authorized even by the example of the Gods. A Marble Statue which
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:107064:62"/>made the publick Devotion among the Heathens, cauſed the paſſion, bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality and the deſpair of a certain young man. <hi>Cherea</hi> in <hi>Torence</hi> forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies himſelf in a criminal diſſign, at the ſight of a Picture of <hi>Jupiters,</hi> which may be, drew the reſpect of all other ſpectatours, Little regard was had to the ſobriety of manners in moſt part of the <hi>Greek</hi> and old <hi>French</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, by reaſon of the vice of the times, wherein they were compoſed. Even the <hi>Aſtrea</hi> and ſome others which have ſollewed, are yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what licentious: but the <hi>Modern</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances (I ſpeak of the good ones) are ſo far from this fault, that one ſhall find not one expreſſion, not one word which may ſhock chaſte ears, nor one ſingle action, which may give offence to Modeſty.</p>
            <p>If any object, that love is there treated of after a faſhion ſo delicate and ſo inſinuating, that the bait of this
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:107064:63"/>dangerours paſſion, enters glibly in young hearts.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that it is ſo far from being dangerous, that it is even in ſome ſort neceſſary, that the young perſons of the World ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this paſſion, that they may ſtop their ears to that which is criminal, and be better enabled to deal with its artifices; and know their conduct in that which has an honeſt and ſacred end; which is ſo true that experience lets us ſee, that ſuch as are leaſt acquainted with Love, are moſt obnoxious to it; and the moſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant are the ſooneſt Duped. Add hereto that nothing ſo much refines and poliſhes the wit, nor conduces ſo much to the faſhioning, and making it fit and proper for the World, as the reading of good Romances. Theſe are the dumb Tutors, which ſucceed to thoſe of the Colledge, and which teach to ſpeak and to live by a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:107064:63"/>more inſtructive, and much more perſwaſive then theirs, and of which may be ſaid, what <hi>Horace</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms of <hi>Homers Iliades,</hi> that they teach morality more effectually, and much better then the moſt able Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>d Urfee</hi> was the firſt who retrived them from Barbarity, and brought them to rules, in his incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable <hi>Aſtrea;</hi> the moſt ingenious and moſt polite work, which ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in this kind, and which has Eclipſed the glory which <hi>Greece, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> had acquired. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he has not diſcouraged thoſe who come after him to undertake what he had enterpriſed; and has not ſo whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engroſſed the publick admiration; but that ſome yet is left for the many excellent Romances, which have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in <hi>France</hi> ſince his. None can without aſtoniſhment look upon thoſe which a Maid, as illuſtrious by
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:107064:64"/>her Modeſty, as by here merit, has pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed under a borrowed Name, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving her ſelf ſo generouſly of that glory which was her due, and notſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a reward but in her vertue: as if while ſhe travailed thus for the honour of our Nation, ſhe would ſpare that ſhame to our ſex. But at the length, time has done her that Juſtice which ſhe denyed herſelf, and has informed us that the Illuſtrious <hi>Baſſa, Grand Cyrus,</hi> and <hi>Clalia</hi> are the Works of Madam <hi>de Scudery;</hi> to the end that hereafter the art of making Romances, which might defend it ſelf againſt ſcrupulous cenſours, not only by the commendations which the Patriarch <hi>Pholius</hi> gives it, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the great examples of thoſe who applyed themſelves, thereto, might alſo juſtifie it ſelf by hers; and which after having been cultivated by Philoſophers, as <hi>Apuleus</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thengoras,</hi> by <hi>Roman</hi> Pretors, as <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenna;</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:107064:64"/>by Conſuls as <hi>Petronius,</hi> by pretendors to the Empire as <hi>Clodius Albinus,</hi> by Prieſts as <hi>Theodorus Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dromus,</hi> by Biſhops as <hi>Heliodorus</hi> and <hi>Achilles Tatius,</hi> by Popes as <hi>Pius Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundus,</hi> who writ the Loves of <hi>Eurya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> and <hi>Lucretia,</hi> by Saints as <hi>John Dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcenus;</hi> it had moreover the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to have been exerciſed by a wiſe and vertuous Maid.</p>
            <p>For your part, Sir, ſince 'tis true, as I have demonſtrated, and <hi>Plutarch</hi> aſſures us, that one of the greateſt charms of a mans ſoul is the tiſſue of a Fable well invented and well rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; what ſucceſs then may not you preſume upon from <hi>Zayde,</hi> where the Adventures are ſo new and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the Narration ſo juſte and ſo polite. I could wiſh for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern I have for that great Prince, whom Heaven has plac'd over us; that we had the Hiſtory of his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:107064:65"/>Reign writ in a ſtyle ſo Noble, and with as much accuratneſs and diſcernment. The Vertue which doth conduct his actions is ſo Heroick, and the Fortune which attends them ſo ſurprizing, that Poſterity would doubt wheter it were Hiſtory or Romance.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:107064:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
